<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the last sicknes and death of Cardinall Bellarmine Who dyed in Rome the seauenteenth day of Septe[m]ber 1621. And of such things as haue happened in, or since his buriall. By C.E. of the Society of Iesus.</title>
            <author>Coffin, Edward, 1571-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853852</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19250</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19250)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1062:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the last sicknes and death of Cardinall Bellarmine Who dyed in Rome the seauenteenth day of Septe[m]ber 1621. And of such things as haue happened in, or since his buriall. By C.E. of the Society of Iesus.</title>
                  <author>Coffin, Edward, 1571-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the English College press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXII  [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.E. = Edward Coffin.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>"In funere Roberti Card. Bellarmini oratio Tarquinii Gallutii Sabini è Societate Iesu" has separate title page which gives imprint date of the original edition printed at Rome as 1621; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint, 1542-1621.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THE LAST SICKNES AND DEATH OF CARDINALL <hi>BELLARMINE.</hi> Who dyed in <hi>Rome</hi> the ſeauenteenth day of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber 1621. And of ſuch things as haue happened in, or ſince his Buriall. <hi>By C. E. of the Society of Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of the English College at Saint-Omer, featuring the seal of the Jesuites or Society of Jesus, a sunburst containing a cross over the letters IHS over three nails</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <q>
                     <p>Dilectus Deo &amp; hominibus Moyſes [<hi>Bellarminus,</hi>] cuius memoria in benedictione est: ſimilem illum fecit in gloria Sanctorum.</p>
                     <bibl>Eccleſiaſt. 45.</bibl>
                     <p>Moyſes (<hi>Bellarmine</hi>) was beloued of God and men, whoſe remembrance is bleſſed: God made him in glory like vnto the Saintes.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                        <body>
                           <p>Permiſſu Superiorum, </p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. DC. XXII.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <hi>THE L. M. M.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>To dye is the courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to dye well, of Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:19250:3"/> Art: that is common to men with beaſts; this proper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods ſeruants alone: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Reg. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>morimur</hi> (ſaid the woman of Thecua vnto Dauid) <hi>&amp; quaſi aqua in terram dilabimur:</hi> we all do dye, and like water fall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth: few dye well, and therefore make a further fall. The Philoſopher will haue Science to ſtand in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, Art in worke; the one in knowledge, the other in practice: and the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite the Art is, and hath the more noble obiect, by ſo much the greater labour and induſtry is required: the Art we ſpeake of hath a moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb facs="tcp:19250:3"/> end, and of ſuch difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it requireth for labour, our vttermoſt endeauour, for tyme our whole life. Art ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Ariſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Phyſi. tex. 79.</note> perfits nature, or doth i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate it. This for imitation hath nothing, becauſe death is nothing but the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nature, the defect and priuation of life, the diuorce and diſſolution of our eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts; and the death of the wicked is tearmed by S.<note place="margin">Bern. ſerm. 26. in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica.</note> 
                     <hi>Bernard,</hi> the mother of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the enemy of glory, the gate of hell, the entrance to perdition: none will imitate, which moſt abhor. Art ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt perfit this deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:19250:4"/> more truly in the maske wherewith it comes couered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the thing it ſelfe which is without horrour, vnles it be of ſuch as our ſelues caſt vpon it. This art of perfiting nature all should learne, but moſt neglect; many precepts are deliuered, but all inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in one, to wit, a conſtant good life, which makes this rough paſſadge plaine, this diſſolution eaſy, this defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity amiable, this diuorce moſt delightfull: <hi>non habemus</hi> (ſaith Saint Ambroſe) <hi>quod in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ambroſ. de bono mortis cap. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>morte metuamus, ſi nihil quod ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it vita commiſit;</hi> there is nothing that we need feare
<pb facs="tcp:19250:4"/> in death, if our life haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nothing that is to be feared.</p>
                  <p>Of this argument all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall books doe treat, and in particuler that vvhich pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely was written of this art by Cardinall Bellarmyne, &amp; vvas the laſt that euer he vvrote: but for that wordes where workes are wanting do blush, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayth, and<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de Patient. Leo ſerm. 1. de San. Laurent.</note> Saint Leo <hi>validiora ſunt exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla quaàm verba, &amp; plenius eſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere docere, quàm voce:</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are of more force to moue then wordes, and more effectuall it is to teach with reall actions then verball diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe;
<pb facs="tcp:19250:5"/> therefore vnto the doctrine of the Cardinall in this behalfe I will adioine his Example, that the one may confirme the other. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, omitting his life, (which others are now in hand to write) I relate only his laſt ſicknes and death; yet from the one we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of the other, becauſe as S. Ambroſe teſtifyeth, <hi>Mors</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ambroſ. ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>vitae eſt teſtimonium,</hi> death is the teſtimony of our life: and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come we ſee a ſaintlike death to follow after a ſynfull life; the priuiledge is rare, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples few; the common ſtile as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noteth
<pb facs="tcp:19250:5"/> is otherwiſe, to wit, that <hi>Mors</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. de Ciuit. Dei lib. 13. cap: 2. in fine.</note> 
                     <hi>bonis bona, malis mala;</hi> a good death befalls to the good, &amp; an ill to the wicked: wherfore the death of this Cardinall being ſo notable as it was, wil not only confirme what he vvrote in his booke of this art, but alſo teſtify for his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life, and shew that what he there ſayd, came not ſo much out of his great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and reading, wherein he was ſingular, as it did <hi>ex abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantia</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 12. Luc. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>cordis,</hi> out of the inward habituall vertue wherwith he was endewed.</p>
                  <p>And for that his doctrine and example do shew &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb facs="tcp:19250:6"/> one and the ſelfe ſame thinge, I meane the great ſanctity of the man, they shal not be ſeparated in the dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that in the argument doe agree. Wheras therfore his Doctrine in our tongue came forth in your Name, his Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple may not paſſe in any other; in which alone you may as in a glaſſe behold how liuely the Child repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the Father, the worke the workeman; ſo far truly, as the Art he wrote may ſeeme to haue beene nothing elſe, but an artificiall deſcription of his owne death that was to enſue. Some will take vpon
<pb facs="tcp:19250:6"/> them to teach others to dye, vvho vvhen they come to it themſelues are to ſeeke a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and ſuch a one may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, that which Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. in Paſtor. ca. vltimo.</note> out of meere humility, ſayd of himſelfe, when he had in his booke called <hi>Pastorale,</hi> deſcribed an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paſtor: <hi>Pulchrum depinxi Paſtorem Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor foedus:</hi> I haue painted a fayre Paſtour, being my ſelfe a foule Painter: I haue taken vpon me to teach that which I neuer learned to doe, and therefore all his teaching as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> well noteth,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. 16. in Matth.</note> ſerueth to no other end then to condemne the teacher: but
<pb facs="tcp:19250:7"/> contrariwiſe vnto the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cardinall we may very fitly apply the wordes of our<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> Sauiour; <hi>Qui fecerit &amp; docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, hic magnus vocabitur in Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no caelorum;</hi> He that shall doe &amp; teach, shall be called great in the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heauen: his doctrine you haue already ſeene in his book; the enſuing narratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I now preſent you will particulerly declare how in his laſt ſicknes &amp; death he did correſpond threunto: to which further I add his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, buriall, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remarkeable euents, few in number out of many, but ſo warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for truth, as grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:19250:7"/> in thinges of this nature, cannot be required.</p>
                  <p>And heere I doe ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme, that in this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I follow no vncertaine ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, no doubtfull aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no flying reportes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground or ſubſiſtence of truth; much leſſe am I mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by any partiall affection to exaggerate or extenuate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing: but faythfully put downe what I ſaw my ſelfe, or vvhat other eye-vvittneſſes haue ſeene, what vpon their owne knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they haue affirmed; many, yea moſt things I haue taken from an Italian letter
<pb facs="tcp:19250:8"/> of this ſubiect written by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iames Minutoli,</hi> a graue, learned, &amp; vertuous man, to Cardinall <hi>Farneſius;</hi> and I vſe the more willingly his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, both for that I know his integrity, and for that by the appointment of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall he continually remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Bellarmyne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of his ſicknes till the laſt gaſp, and ſet down no more then what he ſaw in any particuler: others ſomtymes I alleadge, but of ſuch ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar credit as they are beyond exception, or elſe I would not haue ſo much relyed on their vvordes. Who they are, for
<pb facs="tcp:19250:8"/> the moſt part I name, when I ſet downe any thing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon their atteſtation. But leaſt this Epiſtle ſeeme to long for ſo short a Relation, I will heere conclude it with my prayer, that the death of this famous man may ſerue to put you in mind, with the beginning of the new yeare, not to forget the end of your owne life. This laſt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 1621.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your dutifull poore ſeruant C. E.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:11"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19250:11"/>
                  <head>A TRVE RELATION OF THE DEATH OF <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> of the Society of IESVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Cardinall neyther vvhiles he liued in <hi>Capua,</hi> of which he was Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, nor yet in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> to which he was after called, euer preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his ordinary deuotion, euery day making an houre of meditation, ſaying
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19250:12"/> his Maſſe, the offices of the Breuiary and our B. Lady, the Letanyes to his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; other prayers: yet had he obteyned of the late Pope <hi>Paulus</hi> V. ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, to retyre himſelfe for a whole moneth togeather, euery yeare in the Nouitiate of the Society of <hi>Ieſus</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> And this he did always in Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in which month only, the high Prieſt of the old law did enter into <hi>Sancta Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for death long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hapned.</note> and this high Prieſt prepared his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into that Holy of Holies (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the other was a figure) &amp; not prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe only, but entred alſo in this moneth as we may well thinke into the ſame. In this tyme ſecluding all other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, he made the ſpirituall Exerciſes, beſtowing foure houres dayly in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation; and in the tyme betweene, of which his Maſſe, mattins, beades, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayers did take vp no ſmall part, he wrote the golden books that after he ſet forth of ſpirituall matters, printing euery yeare one, of all which the laſt (as if he had preſaged what was next to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) was the <hi>Art of dying well,</hi> whereof in his beſt health he was neuer vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And this laſt yeare of 1621. as if he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19250:12"/> had receaued <hi>reſponſum mortis,</hi> a moneth ſooner then ordinary, to wit, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Auguſt, he began to thinke, not of a retireme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t only for one moneth, but of a perpetuall ſequeſtration from al ordinary imployments, to attend to that one thing which the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> no leſſe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Hart the water, ſaying,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>Vnampetij à Domino, hanc requiram, vt inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in domo Domini omnibus diebus vitae meae:</hi> One thing haue I deſired of our Lord, that will I ſeeke for, that I may dwell in the howſe of our Lord all the dayes of my life.</p>
                  <p>And to compaſſe the better this his deſire, he made great ſute vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope <hi>Gregory the fifteenth,</hi> to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the Court, from al Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes,<note place="margin">He rety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from the Court.</note> and Congregations, and what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Office ſoeuer, that he might beſtow the ſmall reſidue of his life on God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, alleadging many reaſons for this his reſolution, to wit, his great Age, and that which followes therof, his weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of body, decay of ſight, hearing, &amp; memory; his auerſion from theſe toyles to heauy for ſo weak ſhoulders; and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally his feruent deſire of returning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19250:13"/> to the quiet hauen of Religion, out of which he was taken and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be Cardinal, and in which before his aduancement as the mirrour, &amp; ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of that Order he had liued 38. years togeather, in the continuall practice of Religious diſcipline, and all Chriſtian perfection. Wherfore hauing beene more toſſed in the waues of worldly affayres by reaſon of his dignity, then he would, he now deſired to ſtrike ſaile and in that place to yield his owne ſpirit to God, where firſt God had ſo bountifully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted his holy ſpirit vnto him: there he began his religious life, there he would end it.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> albeit he were loath to looſe the comfort and counſaile of ſo worthy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom the better to enioy he had before called to dwell with him in his pallace; yet ſeeing him ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in his demaund, &amp; the demaund in it ſelfe ſo reaſonable, at length yielded therunto; and forthwith the Cardinall left the Court, returned to the Nouiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of the Society, &amp; diſmiſſed the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of his family, but yet ſo as they might remayne ſtill in the pallace and in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19250:13"/> the ſame ſtate they were before vnder him, and at his charge, vntill they could place themſelues in ſome other ſeruice. Which tydings although it grieued them all, both for that they ſaw the loſſe they were like to find in the exchange, and for the great loue and moſt deere reſpect which they bare vnto his perſon, from whome nothing but his commaund, or their own death could haue drawn the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet ſeeing the conſtant &amp; reſolute mind of their Lord, euery one bare the Croſſe as he could, more applauding his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue then their owne fortune in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce; which the more grieued them in that they iudged him to haue leſſe need of any other preparation to dye well, who euen from his infancy had ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed himſelfe in that Art, which by practice he had obſerued more then threeſcore yeares, before euer he left any thing written of that ſubiect in his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted booke.</p>
                  <p>Being now arryued at the harbour of his ſo long, and much deſired repoſe on the 25. of Auguſt laſt, when the feaſt of S. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> is kept in <hi>Rome,</hi> one<note place="margin">He falleth ſicke.</note> buſines of moment yet remayned in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19250:14"/> Congregation of the <hi>Indice,</hi> which much required his prefence for diſpatch, and the Cardinals being now aſſembled on the 28. day, thither alſo he repayred, and after that it was ended, he took his leaue and farefull of them all. All ſeemed to be ſory therat: ſome would haue perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to continue, but as the <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list</hi> ſayth of our Sauiour, <hi>Ipſe faciem ſuam firmauit, vt iret in Hieruſalem,</hi> he ſtedfaſtly<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> bent his face to goe to Hieruſalem, his mind was on heauen, he would not looke backe or be withdrawne from his iourney, which indeed was ſhorter then any one (or perhaps himſelfe) did ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine: for that very night being the feaſt of S. <hi>Augustine</hi> (to which holy Doctour he was very ſpecially deuoted, as all his workes doe teſtify) he fell ſicke and was taken with a very ſharp and violent fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that bereaued him of his ſenſes for the tyme. Which rough entrance of the diſeaſe in one of his yeares made all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, and moſt of all his Phiſitians (for there came foure euery day vnto him) who apprehended euident danger, and much grieued at this miſcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; but their griefe was not greater then his ioy, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19250:14"/> deſired nothing more then to leaue the world, as preſently after appeared.</p>
                  <p>For when this fit was paſt, with great alacrity of mynd he began to diſcourſe of the great gladnes and comfort he had, for that he was ſo neere his home, or as he did alwayes in this ſicknes call it, <hi>a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heauen Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines howſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Caſa mia,</hi> to my howſe: and worthily did he call it his howſe, for as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth of the militant Church on earth: <hi>non magis est domus tua, quàm domus vhi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 10. in Ioannem.</note> 
                     <hi>ſalutem aeternam:</hi> There is no howſe more thine, then that howſe where thou haſt euerlaſting ſaluation: ſo might he no leſſe fittly ſay of the triumphant howſe, Kingdome, and inheritance of all Gods ſeruants on earrh, which he with ſo long and infatigable labour had purchaſed, that it was his houſe, for there had he fixt his hopes, there had he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp al his wealth, there was his hart, his treaſure, all his deſired good: to this world he was not ſo much a ſtranger as an enemy. And although that euen here Honour did follow his noble labours as the ſhadow the body; yet did none more fly from it, none more contemne and condemne it, then he. The Cardinall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19250:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19250:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19250:16"/> proceeding in his diſcourſe ſayd and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated theſe wordes: <hi>ſatis di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vixi,</hi> I haue liued long inough, it is tyme to depart hence and reſt with God in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace. What I haue to do more in this vvorld? I am now feeble and fit for nothing; I am only a meere burden &amp; trouble to my ſelfe &amp; others. And then further declared, hovv he did loath and abhorre, and had ſtill loathed &amp; abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the courſe of this vvorld, that men vvere ſo deeply plunged in the deſire of temporall and tranſitory things; grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at their prepoſterous proceedings, that their endeauours vvere not directed to their right end, and that God was not ſought for, knovvne, nor glorified as he ought to be: and this point piercing indeed his hart, he concluded vvith ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that God had ſhewed him now a ſpirituall ſauour to call him avvay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it vvas bitter and diſtaſtfull vnto him to ſtay any longer heere &amp;c. Thus vvith more to this effect did he then ſpeake, and of theſe things only vvas his continuall ſpeach.</p>
                  <p>The Phiſitians expecting the iſſue of the diſeaſe, and nature thereof, found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19250:16"/> it to be a continuall feuer <hi>per ſubintran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> with proportion of a double Terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, the one more exceſſiue then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the former bereaued him of his ſenſes, the other vvas much more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. And truly it ſeemes this bereaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to haue been ſent him for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manifeſtation of his vertue, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he no leſſe edifyed others that ſavv<note place="margin">His extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of ſicknes, &amp; ſingular patience.</note> him, then he did in the other, but rather much more; for according to the rule of the Philoſopher <hi>In repentinis cognoſcitur habitus,</hi> our diſpoſition is beſt knovvne by ſuddaine euents: ſo the violent and ſuddaine pulls did ſhevv the habits of his Saint-like mynde, hauing no other ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect therein then to make him recurre to his prayers, which he did as ſoon as they began, and ſay them as farre as he vvas able. When this vehemency vvas a little relented he would make the ſigne of the Croſſe, and begin another prayer; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much as once in all theſe extreme fits ſpeaking any idle word, or ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt ſigne of any impatience. In ſo much as my ſelfe in company of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers often viſiting him, and that at ſuch tymes as he was in this feuer, I doe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19250:17"/> proteſt, that I neuer ſaw man in his beſt health, repoſe more quietly, or make leſſe ſhew of feeling the force of any diſeaſe, then alwayes I ſaw him in this. For the moſt part his armes were decently layed a Croſſe on his breſt, he neuer mouing (vnles he were willed) any part of his body, neuer ſighing, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer complayning, no though his tongue were ſcorched with the raging heat of the ague, did he euer ſo much as call for drinke, or once offered to refreſh his mouth; ſo as the beholders could make no other iudgement of him, but that which the diſciples made of <hi>Lazarus: ſi dormit ſaluus erit,</hi> if he ſleep he will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer;<note place="margin">Ioan. 11.</note> for his magnanimity was ſuch he rather ſeemed to ſleep then to be ſicke and thereby gaue greater ſignes of life then death.</p>
                  <p>But notwithſtanding this his great courage &amp; patience, the diſeaſe ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the increaſe cauſed the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s according to their wont to warne<note place="margin">His wil &amp; teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> him to make his laſt will &amp; teſtament, to the end he might be the more free in thinking on the life to come, towardes which he did now draw on apace. To
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19250:17"/> this ſuggeſtion he made no other anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were, but that all was diſpatched, his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament was made, his goods diſpoſed, euery thing determined many yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go; adding withall that he had giuen to euery one of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſomwhat accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their degree and place which they had in his ſeruice, and according to that ſmall ability he had to gratify them withall. For other things, although he once intended to make no wil, as mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of that pouerty which he had vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Religion; yet afterward leaſt ſuch ſmall things as he left, ſhould come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other handes then of poore men, he made a ſhort Will agreable to his little wealth, which I ſhal after ſet down, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his Order (the Society of Ieſus I meane) heyre not to his wealth which was none at al, but as he ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ſicknes, <hi>propenſae voluntatis ac pauperta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis meae,</hi> of my affection and pouerty: &amp; he might well ſay of his pouerty, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which he had left for his owne diet (which was alwayes very meane) and the wages of his ſeruants, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready beſtowed the reſt on the poore, in ſo much as he had not inough left
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19250:18"/> him for his buriall and exequies, in caſe the Pope had not fauoured him, as after ſhalbe ſhewed: and the Will it ſelfe vvas ſuch as might beſeeme <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> but to others will ſeeme perhaps as ſtrange as any that hath beene made for many yeares by a Cardinall.</p>
                  <p>Now though this mention of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his laſt Will gaue him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the danger of his diſeaſe, yet he much deſired to be more particulerly enformed thereof, and to that end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted all the Phiſitians to tell him plainly in what ſtate he was, aſſuring them all that he feared not death but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it: and ſo far (quoth he) I am from all feare as that I fynd a ſpeciall comfort to thinke theron; yea life it ſelfe would be more grieuous vnto me then death. Wherfore I pray you aduertiſe me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes, that I may receaue the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments ere I depart. Vpon theſe words the fourth day of his ſicknes it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted amongſt the Doctours whether it were not expedient that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the B. Sacrament of the Altar <hi>per modum viatici;</hi> and they iudged it not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to giue it him in that manner,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19250:18"/> but only by way of ordinary communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating, and their reaſon was becauſe he might yet continue for many dayes, and in caſe ſome ſodden accident ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him, this receauing might ſuffice for the other.</p>
                  <p>Vpon this warning giuen, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared himſelfe to Confeſſion, &amp; in ſuch<note place="margin">He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> manner as if that Confeſſion vvere to be the laſt that euer he ſhould make in this life; and ſuch was the innocency of the man, that albeit he were in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſenſe, yet could he hardly find what to confeſſe; in ſo much as his Ghoſtly Father was in ſome perplexity as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting matter of Abſolution, till by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to his life paſt he found ſome ſmal defects of which he abſolued him: and when the B. Sacrament was brought he would needs riſe to receaue it, as he did, and proſtrated himſelfe on the ground with ſingular deuotion and humility, to the great edification and amazement of all the beholders. And this his piety vpon euery occaſion did manifeſt it ſelfe in all his ſicknes, in ſo much as he deſired the Phiſitians leaue to ſay the Office of his Breuiary, and that ſo earneſtly, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19250:19"/> the Doctours, though they denied that (as a worke to great for his weakenes,) yet to ſatisfy his importunity they gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unted that in lieu therof he might ſay his Beades, but with ſome pawſe betweene euery decade, leaſt his too ſerious appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation might hurt his head. And ſeeing that no more would be graunted him, he ſayd to thoſe about him: Me thinkes I am become a meere Secular man, and am no more Religious, for I neyther ſay Office, nor Maſſe, I make no pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I doe no good at all; and this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to afflict him more then his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which yet was moſt violent and mortall.</p>
                  <p>After meate all his recreation was to heare the liues of Saintes read vnto<note place="margin">He cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the liues of Saints to be read vnto him.</note> him, eſpecially of Biſhops, and aboue all of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> and in the hearing their rare and eminent vertues, he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes weep and ſigh after that perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life to which they had ſo happily arriued, and from which (ſuch vvas his humility) he thought himſelfe to be much further of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was; for he could not but be neere them whom for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares he had moſt diligently follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19250:19"/> Beſides this griefe conceaued for himſelfe &amp; his own vnworthines, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing alſo ſeemed to afflict him, to wit, the continuall watch in the night with him, for he would ordinarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of ſuch as he ſaw about him in the mourning, vvhether they had wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vvith him all that night; &amp; if they ſayd yea, then would he reply; ſo much trouble, and of ſo many, for my ſake! For me, I ſay, that am but a vvorme, a poore wretch and fit for nothing! and if he ſavv more togeather with him, he would ſay, one is ſufficient to watch, let the reſt ſleepe, and let another watch whiles he doth ſleepe, the trouble of ſo many is a trouble vnto me vvho deſerue not ſo much attendance. Likevviſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note place="margin">His chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the poore.</note> he ſaw any extraordinary thing brought him to eate, as chickens or the like, he would ſay, that ſuch expenſe was ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon him, and would be better on the poore, whome he ſo loued, and was ſo bountifull vnto them, as he left himſelfe ſo little, as could hardly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne him and ſatisfy his family: &amp; for that on his death-bed he was ſo carefull of them, it will not be amiſſe to put
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19250:20"/> downe ſome example of his life in this kind, &amp; it ſhalbe the firſt he did after his promotion, by which ſome coniecture may be made of the reſt which I leaue in ſilence.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. ſoone after he had giuen him his Cardinals Hat, made him alſo Archbiſhop of <hi>Capua:</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he left <hi>Rome,</hi> and like a true Paſtor repayred to his flocke there to reſide, &amp; diſcharge all the dutyes of his function. And firſt of all finding the reuenews of<note place="margin">A liberall allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> that Church to amount to three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds ſterling, he preſently gaue vnto the poore, two thouſand, mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning himſelfe and his family with the reſt, which for one of that ranke was very little, but he would no more; and when after the death of the ſaid <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with other Cardinals he was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre to <hi>Rome,</hi> for the election of the new Pope, the poore came flocking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, crying, and ſaying, that his departute would be their vndoing. Not ſo (quoth the Cardinall) for my going to <hi>Rome</hi> will not I hope take away my rents, and if they remayne to me, they ſhal reſt where they are with you. They
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19250:20"/> all replied with teares that they thought he ſhould returne no more (as indeed he did not) and then that the rents ſhould be neyther his nor theirs. And my ſelfe haue ſeene often in <hi>Rome</hi> when the Cardinal went abroad, at his returne all the lower entry of his houſe full of poore people, on whome he beſtowed his ordinary almes. And in particular, which I may not omit, one ſhrouetyde an Engliſh man halfe diſtracted of his<note place="margin">He giues halfe of his dinner vnto a poore En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman.</note> ſenſes came boldly to the Cardinall (for neyther his dores, eares, or purſe were ſhut from the poore) and demaunded ſome reliefe, hauing as he ſayd nothing to eate: the good Cardinall without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further deliberation cauſed his owne dinner to be deuided in two, &amp; gaue the one halfe thereof vnto the ſayd Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and dined himſelfe on the other: and my ſelfe coming that very day to the Cardinall, was aduertiſed thereof. But examples heereof are ſo many, as would make a volume, and I meane not to diſgreſſe any further from his death.</p>
                  <p>Many other vertues were noted in him at this tyme, and ſo many as that this ſickneſſe may ſeeme to haue beene
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19250:21"/> the abridgement of all which he had exerciſed in his life before. For beſides the aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned courteſy in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity<note place="margin">His great courteſy &amp; reſpect vnto all.</note> to all that did viſit him, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of mynd was admirable. And for the firſt he neuer reſpected his owne inconuenience, payne or trouble, in ſo much as not only to Cardinals and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, but to any other that came to ſee him (and there came many) he would take off his night-cap, lift himſelfe vp in his bed, ſpeake vnto euery one more or leſſe as the quality of the perſon, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he ſpake of did require; &amp; wold neuer endure that any ſhould ſtand bare headed in his preſence, and this euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the two laſt dayes of his life, when nature being far ſpent, the feuer with the decay of his ſtrength ſtil encreaſing, he eyther attended not to ſuch as came, but vnto his prayers, or elſe his eyes and eares fayling, he neyther ſaw nor heard them, vnles they ſpake ſomwhat lowd: and euen to his owne ſeruants he bare that reſpect, as he would endure much rather then put them to any trouble. And when F. <hi>Minutoli</hi> once told him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat no man held it for a trouble to ſerue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19250:21"/> him, and ſuch as there attended were his owne ſeruants; he anſwered only to theſe laſt words, &amp; ſaid they are not my ſeruants but my brethren, brethren they are, and for ſuch I eſteeme them.</p>
                  <p>And that indeed he eſteemed them more like his brethren then ſeruants ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes appeared, eſpecially if any of his houſe fell ſicke as there did two, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell ſicke himſelfe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or then his cuſtome wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to go to their cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to ſit and talke with them, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, &amp; euery way to aſſiſt &amp; help them. And touching theſe two, the laſt of which <hi>Matthaeus Tortus</hi> was one, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an attendant of his chamber, this memorable thing is recorded; that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Tortus</hi> was exceeding ſicke, and held to be in great danger of death, and the other but in the entrance of his diſeaſe which he ſeemed not much to regard, yet the Cardinall hauing ſeene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both ſayd, that <hi>Tortus</hi> ſhould recouer and the other dye, which as it ſeemed ſtrange to all that heard it, who ſaw great ſignes of death in the one, &amp; ſcarce the appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of any ſicknes in the other; ſo the euent proued to be true: for the later within
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19250:22"/> few dayes departted this life, and <hi>Tortus</hi> is yet liuing, and in perfect health.</p>
                  <p>His reſignation and indifferency of<note place="margin">His reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation &amp; indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> of mind was very exact, without all contradiction or reply: whatſoeuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whatſoeuer was determined, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing troubled his mind, no exception was made, one thing only excepted (if yet that thing be ſubiect to exception) for thus it hapned. He hauing from the beginning of his ſicknes prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to dye, it fel out that the ſeauenth day held by the Phiſitians for <hi>Critical,</hi> he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſomwhat better: much ioy was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued therat, &amp; the ſame ſignified vnto the Cardinal, who weighing the matter in another balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, was ſomwhat trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with this ſoden reſolution, and ſaid myldly vnto the Doctors: I had thought at this tyme to haue gone to my houſe and home, and now I ſee that you will hinder me: I pray you let me goe. Their anſwere was, that it belonged vnto their office to preſerue his life as long as they could, and was pleaſing vnto God, and he alſo was bound therein to concurre with them, to doe as they ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, and be contented to ſtay in this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19250:22"/> world vntill that God ſhould otherwiſe diſpoſe. Well then (quoth the Cardinal) his will be done: but if the choice were in my handes, I ſhould rather dye then liue; wherfore doe as you will, I ſhall follow your direction. And when the Phiſitians were gone, he ſeemed ſo much to be diſcomforted, that his Attendants vvere all mooued to comfort him, and that no leſſe then ordinarily men vſe to comfort others that are to dye, &amp; would longer liue.</p>
                  <p>Agayne, at another tyme vvhen three of his foure Phiſitians had conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and determined to make tryall of a nevv remedy, he ſayd vnto them: Will you not yet let me goe? Ah let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone novv it is high time. Fa. <hi>Minutoli</hi> anſvvered and ſayd, the Rule of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety doth bynde vs in ſicknes to obey the Phiſitians; he had no ſooner named the <hi>Rule,</hi> but the other recalling his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wordes ſayd: you ſay well, there is a <hi>Rule,</hi> let them appoint what they wil, I wil do whatſoeuer they wil haue me: ſo punctual he was in obſeruing the Rules of the Society in all thinges, eyther for life or death, with, or againſt his owne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19250:23"/> inclination. Some neere perhaps vvill ſay, that notvvithſtanding he loathed this life, thirſted after heauen, and vvould gladly be vvith God, yet he was not to wiſh for his ovvne death. To vvhich idle fancy I anſvvere vvith S. <hi>Augustine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. lib. 2. in Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. in fine.</note> 
                     <hi>Non eſt iniustum homimi iuſto optare mortem, quando amariſsima eſt vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a: ſed ſi Deus optatam non dederit, non erit iuſtum niſi tolerare eam amariſsiman vitam:</hi> it is lawfull for a good man to vviſh for death vvhen as life it ſelfe is very bitter vnto him: but if God yield not vnto his deſire, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully refuſe to endure his bitter life. So he. And ſo the Cardinall although he vviſhed for death vvas yet reſigned vnto Almighty God, to vndergo the longer endurance of a bitter life.</p>
                  <p>But leauing his vertues for a vvhile vvhich euery vvhere occurre to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, let vs a little behold vvhat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things hapned in the vvhole courſe and ſucceſſe of his ſicknes, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vvherof it vvas thought good for auoiding of recourſe to ſpeak little ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; to extenuate the ſame as not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but rather ſome caſuall indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this perſuaſion continued for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19250:23"/> three or foure dayes till the Pope truly<note place="margin">Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him on his deathbed.</note> enformed by his owne Phiſitian who repayred dayly vnto the Cardinall, &amp; by the <hi>Generall</hi> of the Society in what ſtate he was, came in perſon to viſit him the fifth day of his diſeaſe, for then all apprehended the matter as it was, &amp; made no other accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but to looſe him. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Cardinal ſaw his Holines enter into his chamber, he ſayd with the good <hi>Centurion, Non ſum dignus, vt intres ſub tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>meum,</hi> I am not worthy that you ſhould enter vnder my roofe; with other wordes of great dutifulnes and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: &amp; when the Pope ſhewed the griefe of mynd he conceaued for his ſicknes, and how much he eſteemed his loſſe; the other anſwered as he had alwayes done, that he had liued long inough, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired no longer reſpit on earth, &amp; I will pray God (quoth he) to graunt<note place="margin">The humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory.</note> your Holines as long life (for he is ten yeares younger then <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> was) as he hath vnto me. The Pope replied (but not in ſo lowd a voyce as the Cardinall could heare him) I haue more need of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> meritts, then of his yeares. Many wordes paſt betweene them of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19250:24"/> great affection in the one, and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue humility in the other. The Pope af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had twice moſt louingly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him, being to depart, ſayd that he would pray to God that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer: not (quoth the Cardinall) that I may recouer being now fit for nothing, but that Gods will and pleaſure may be done eyther for life or death. After that the Pope was gone, he ſeemed to be much more cheerful then he was before, the cauſe whereof he diſcloſed vnto F. <hi>Minutoli</hi> ſaying: Now truly doe I well hope that I ſhall dye, for the Popes are neuer known to haue viſited Cardinalls but when they were in danger of death, or rather paſt all hope of life, to which effect he alleadged diuers examples.</p>
                  <p>Remayning therfore in this ioyfull hope, when diuers of the Society came to him and offered to ſay maſſe and pray for him, he would very louingly thank them all, but ſtill accepted their curteſy with this <hi>Caueat,</hi> that they ſhould not pray for his longer life, but contrariwiſe<note place="margin">His deſire to leaue the world.</note> that he might ſoone make an exchange therof for a better, that his paſſage might be ſafe and ſoone. The cauſe of this his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19250:24"/> deſire he alleadged to be, for that novv he had prepared himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and knew not for the tyme to come what in the reſt of his life, if it were prolonged, might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him: for, ſayd he, I haue knowne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, who if at ſome tyme when they were wel diſpoſed had departed this life, had beene in very happy ſtate, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering their health, fell after very far from that feruour, and dyed ſo deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in humane iudgement they may be rather thought the children of perdition then life: Now therfore (quoth he) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am ready, why ſhould I liue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and expoſe my ſelfe to ſuch an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard? Now nothing troubles my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for God (his goodneſſe be ſtill thanked therfore) hath ſo preſerued me hitherto, as that I doe not remember in the whole courſe of my liue euer to haue committed any ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalous action, which perhaps if I ſhould life longer, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall me, for weakenes of body drawes oftentymes with it weakenes of mind, by which good men haue beene ſeene to haue relented from their former vigour and vertue. This with more to this effect did he ſpeake to expreſſe the cauſe why
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19250:25"/> he deſired the diſſolution of his earthly tabernacle, which was no other, but that leaſt through the frailty of body &amp; mind he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eerafter offend God, whome hitherto, <hi>in ſanctitate &amp; iustitia omnibus die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>vitae ſuae,</hi> in holines and vertue all the dayes of his lire, he had ſo carefully, ſo continually ſerued, and whome now he had rather dye then diſpleaſe.</p>
                  <p>This his feruent deſire grounded on the foreſaid motiue was ſo imprinted in his hart, and fixed therein ſo deeply, as<note place="margin">His diſeaſe is found to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</note> euen then when his violent ague berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him of his ſenſes he was often heard to ſay: <hi>Signore, vorrei andare a caſa mia: quando ſarà quel giorno che io venga al vostr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Regno &amp;c.</hi> O Lord I would gladly go to my howſe; when will that day be when I may come to thy Kingdome? And the eleauenth day after his ſicknes he ſayd vnto all his Phiſitians: When ſhal I heare from you that happy newes that I muſt depart to another life? when ſhall I be deliuered from this body of death? They anſwered as before, not ſo long as they could keep him aliue. Well (quoth he) God ſees my deſire, and how willing I am to come vnto him. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19250:25"/> indeed <hi>non est fraudatus deſiderio ſuo,</hi> God heard his prayer, and that very night he was ſeene to yex or ſob in ſuch manner, as a learned Phiſitian watching with him held it for mortall, and forthwith aduertiſed the <hi>Generall</hi> (for ſo had the Cardinall before willed them, when they ſhold perceaue him in euident dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) who came early the next morning, and ſeeing how matters went, thought it beſt, plainly to acquaint him with the truth, and ſayd vnto him: My Lord, I thinke that the end of this ſicknes will be the end your life, and by all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode you cannot eſcape long, for the Phiſitians now giue a very ill cenſure of your diſeaſe, vpon ſome ſignes they haue ſeene, and more and more diſcerne in you: ſo as it ſeemes Almighty God will call you vnto him, and you ſhall do well to make your ſelfe ready, and diſpoſe of what you haue, the time is ſhort, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes are dangerous.</p>
                  <p>At this vnexpected, but much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red meſſage, the good Cardinall reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed<note place="margin">His great ioy at the newes of his death.</note> with inward ioy, preſently with cheerfull countenance, and vndaunted courage brake forth into theſe wordes:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19250:26"/> 
                     <hi>Buona nuoua, buona nuoua, ô che buona nuoua è questa!</hi> that is, good news, good news, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> what good newes are theſe! Lo the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of an innocent mynde, of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſeruant, and Apoſtolicall man, who ioyed in death, wherat others doe trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and made that his gaine which worldly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſteeme their greateſt loſſe: but theſe graces are not beſtowed, but vpon ſuch only as haue wholy beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues vpon God, for ſuch alone, as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith (<hi>conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>platione quadam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributionis</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gregor. 24. in Iob. cap. 7. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe finem.</note> 
                     <hi>inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae, etiam priuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carne expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantur, hilareſcunt; &amp; dum vetustatis debitum ſoluunt, noui iam muneris laetitia perfruuntur</hi>) by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation of that which their ſoule receaues within, doe, before they leaue their bodyes, become cheerfull; &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then whiles they are yielding to the diſſolution of their old nature, doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the comfort of their new reward. So he of the vertuous in generall, which in this worthy man we ſee ſo particularly accompliſhed, who ſtill prayed with the Apoſtle and ſayd, <hi>Cupio diſsolui, &amp; eſse cum</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Christo:</hi> I deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>After this ioyfull exclamation, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rning
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19250:26"/> his ſpeach vnto F. <hi>Generall,</hi> as anſwering vnto that which he had ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, he ſayd: For diſpoſing of my thinges I haue nothing left to diſpoſe, &amp; it grieueth me that I haue nothing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon the Society, for I feare much that in making you mine heyres, as if I<note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> had ſomething to leaue you, I ſhall but charge you with new debts, which for my ſake you will be forced to diſcharge. The <hi>Generall</hi> replyed, that therein he ſhould not trouble himſelfe, he had left the Society ſo much, and ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured it with his name and immortall labours, as it eſteemed that treaſure more then all the riches of the world. Well the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid the Cardinall, I came hither to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow one whole yeare in preparing my ſelfe to dye, but if it pleaſe not God that I beſtow any more time heerin, neyther truly ſhal it pleaſe me; and therfore your meſſage of death is moſt gratefull &amp;c. After this he cauſed one to reade vnto him the death of S. <hi>Charles Borromaeus,</hi> as<note place="margin">S. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus.</note> deſirous in his owne to imitate it; which being ended he deſired to receaue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of holy Church, &amp; that as ſoone as might be, leaſt after he ſhould be leſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19250:27"/> able for indiſpoſition both of body and minde to receaue them, and to preuent alſo any ſuddayne accident that might in this weaknes take him away, ere he had armed himſelfe with this ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſoueraigne defence.<note place="margin">He recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Forth with all thinges were made ready for receauing of the B. Sacrament of the Altar for his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> which was miniſtred vnto him by the handes of the <hi>Generall,</hi> and receaued with exceeding deuotion of the Cardinall: for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his extreme weaknes of body, he would needs agayne, as he had done before, riſe out of his bed, and kneele on the ground to receaue it; and ſo earneſt he was to receaue it in this reuerent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as it was not poſſible, without his great griefe and diſtaſt, to hinder him. The <hi>Generall</hi> perceauing his will ſo fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently bent on that deuotion, wold not withſtand him therein, leaſt the inward griefe might more afflict his mind then that exteriour action endomage his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: wherfore he receaued it kneeling on the ground, with ſingular humility; &amp; after ſome collection made according to his wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which endured for ſome while,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19250:27"/> he began to talke with the Generall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his buriall, and the manner of his funeralls, which he did with ſo great peace of minde, &amp; ſo familiarly, as if in his health he had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of going to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or ſome other light and ordinary matter.</p>
                  <p>Much he deſired to be buryed like a Religious man; &amp; all his diſcourſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">A true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Spirit.</note> thereunto. For firſt he requeſted to be buryed in the common vault vnder the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (for ſo in <hi>Italy</hi> they vſe to bury) where others of that Order are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily layed; then that his funeralls might be plaine, &amp; in ſuch manner as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he had dyed in the Society; and had neuer been aduanced, being very earneſt that no pompe or ſplendour accuſtomed for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cardinalls might be made for him; that they would not open and enbalme his body, but bury it entiere as they doe others; and finally that his dead body preſently after his death might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied ſecretly to the Fathers Church cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Caſa profeſſa,</hi> &amp; there be interred, none intermedling with the Exequies but the ſaid Fathers, as they vſe to do for their own in ſuch caſes. The <hi>Generall</hi> not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19250:28"/> to trouble him, being in thoſe tearmes, made no ſemblance of any miſlike, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he thought it not conuenient that all ſhould paſſe in that order. Wherefore conferring with the Pope therin ſome things were reuerſed, for his Holines would haue him buryed like a Cardinall, but with meaner pomp; he would haue him embalmed, &amp; would haue the other Cardinalls to be preſent, ſending alſo his owne <hi>Quiristers</hi> thither; in the reſt he condeſcended to what he had determined, as after ſhalbe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day ſome ſix or ſeauen houres after his receauing, he demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">He is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyled.</note> the other; and laſt Sacrament of the ſicke, <hi>Extreme Vnction</hi> I meane, which he requeſted the ſooner to receaue, becauſe he would be ſure, he ſayd, not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of it, or to take it when he ſhould not know well what he did take; he was now in his perfect ſenſes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might receaue it with deuotion; as he did, and anſwered <hi>Amen,</hi> with great compunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hart at ech ſeueral vncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and now with greater ſerenity of mynd then before he expected his laſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19250:28"/> cal, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Lord to take him out of this vale of miſery and bring him where he might ſee, <hi>Bona Domini in terra</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 370</note> 
                     <hi>viuentium,</hi> the ioy of our Lord in the land of the liuing.</p>
                  <p>And for that ſome Sectaries of theſe dayes had bruted abroad that he had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured their cauſe (of which he was the<note place="margin">He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Fayth.</note> deſtruction) or had recalled ſome of his opinions; he entreated Fa. <hi>Andraeas Eudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Ioannes</hi> then preſent, that he would teſtify in ſome writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> record, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he (to wit the Cardinall) had written or printed concerning matters of Fayth againſt the Heretikes and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes of theſe tymes, that now on his deathbed, he did moſt reſolutely auouch againe, ratify, and confirme the ſame, &amp; cauſed this his atteſtation to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſubſcribed by diuers that were preſent, as by his two Nephevvs, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Fathers of the Society, &amp; ſome of his owne ſeruants; and I doubt not but the ſayd Father out of the great loue and dutifull reſpect which he alwayes bare the Cardinall, will very willingly diſcharge this debt in ſome work that he ſhall ſhortly ſet foorth, if his health doe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19250:29"/> not hinder him, as it hath done many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his moſt commendable, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable endeauours.</p>
                  <p>Being thus armed for his laſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, and in great tranquillity and peace of mynd, he began agayne to caſt backe his eyes on his life paſt to ſee what therein might trouble his conſcience, or breed any feare in him at that ſtraite ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before God, which now hourely he did expect to be called vnto: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">See the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience of this moſt holy and innocent Cardinall.</note> all his diſcuſſion &amp; ſearch he ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Father <hi>Minutoli,</hi> that no one thing ſo much troubled him of all that he had done in his life paſt, as that he had left his Church &amp; Archbiſhopricke of <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a,</hi> where by his continuall reſidence he might haue done more good to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory of God, and good of thoſe ſoules committed vnto his charge, then in any other place; &amp; that heere in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſeemed that he had loſt his time, and had done nothing of any weight or moment: wheras yet he was well knowne to leeſe no tyme that he could well ſpare, &amp; was imployed in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of moſt importance which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the whole Church, the proper office
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19250:29"/> of a Cardinall, as the ſayd Father told him, which is not ſo much to attend to a particular member, as to the common profit of the whole body: for as Saint <hi>Leo</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leo. epiſt.</note> will noteth: <hi>publica praeferenda ſunt proprijs, &amp; ibi intelligenda est ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io vtiliatis, vbi vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat cura communis.</hi> Moreouer, ſayd the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you can haue no ſcruple in this matter which you did by commaund of the Pope, whome you were bound by your rule to obey, &amp; conſequently your aboad not being of your ſeeking but his enforcing, it cannot be imputed to you as a fault; but contrarivviſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, as proceedinge from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Obedience which you could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, ſayd the Cardinall, ſo the<note place="margin">Bellarmin would not leaue his Church and keep the rents.</note> matter paſſed, and I plainly ſignifyed vnto <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, that I could not in conſcience, not reſiding in the place, keep the Archbiſhopricke in my handes, &amp; therfore deſired him in caſe he would haue me to remaine in <hi>Rome,</hi> that I might altogeather renounce the Archbiſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, that men might not iuſtly charge me, and with reaſon ſay: He hath forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his wife, and yet keepes her dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19250:30"/> and therfore leauing the one, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the other, and yielded vp all entierly as well charge as profit into the Popes handes, without euer making any mention of allowance for my ſelfe to be deducted from thence. So he. And yet he might haue ſubſtituted a Suffragan, and kept at leaſt two parts of three, had he beene ſo diſpoſed; but he renounced all freely, and wholy, and after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation made ſute to the Pope to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him ſomwhat for his maintenance, hauing now only left him the title of a Biſhop without a Church, the dignity of a Cardinall without any liuing, and charge of ſeruantes without hauing ſo much rent as to pay his Cooke; the Pope allowed him, as he had in <hi>Capua</hi> allowed himſelfe, foure thouſad crowns, and for that one part of this ſumme was leuied by way of penſion on the rents of the Church of <hi>Capua,</hi> though it were done much againſt his will, he neuer ceaſed til his death, yearly out of his ſmal allowance to beſtow ſomething on the poore Monaſteryes of that Citty; ſo as al this matter paſſed with ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of heroicall magnanimity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19250:30"/> on his behalfe, and in moſt honorable manner. But for that he had learned of his deare Maiſter <hi>B. Fa. Ignatius,</hi> not only to ſeek the glory of God, but <hi>maiorem Dei gloriam,</hi> the greater glory of God in all thinges; &amp; becauſe he thought that he might haue done more good in <hi>Capua</hi> then in <hi>Rome,</hi> therfore did he ſorrow, &amp; had this remorſe. O noble Biſhop, O zealous mynd, O rare example worthy of the name, renowne and eminent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Bellarmyne!</hi> How holy was his life not ſtayned with mortall ſinne? How ſecure a conſcience, that had at his death no ſcruple, but for the exchange of one good worke for another, and that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon him by an ineuitable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund? What ſhall I heere ſay, but that <hi>fecit mirabilia in vita ſua,</hi> he hath, euen<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 31.</note> in this mortall life, done vvonderfull things.</p>
                  <p>This ſcruple being remoued, and<note place="margin">Scipio Card. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellutiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> his mynd quieted, there remayned one difficulty touching his temporall eſtate, to wit for repayment of his Cardinalls Ring; for effecting of which he vſed the help of the Cardinall of S. <hi>Suſanna</hi> to his Holines, alleadging this reaſon, that <hi>non
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19250:31"/> erat ſoluendo,</hi> for he had not wher withall to bury him, much leſſe to pay that debt; adding further that the ſame grace had beene before graunted vnto Cardinall <hi>Baronius,</hi> and another Cardinall. Vnto vvhich requeſt the Pope moſt willingly yielded; and further at the requeſt of the <hi>Generall,</hi> for the Cardinall ſought it not, the Pope alſo condeſcended to giue a penſion of three hundred crownes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his two nephews, &amp; had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les graunted more, if more had beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded; but the Cardinall little myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his nephews or earthly preferments, hauing his thoughts on heauen, which he alvvayes called his Home; there was his reward layed vp: <hi>Et merces eius mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na nimis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it vvas knovvne in the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that the Pope had beene with the Cardinal, that he had taken his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> that he vvas anneyled, and that there<note place="margin">meanes to ſee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eke Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall.</note> was no hope left of longer life, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it vvas, not to only heare the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reports which all made of him, but to ſee the meanes and inuentions vſed, &amp; that by men of Quality, to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Some ſued vnto the Cardinalls
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19250:31"/> and great Perſonages; ſome intreated the Fathers; ſome vſed the help of his ſeruants, and others made other deuiſes, and this not only to ſee him, but to kiſſe his handes, his head, or ſome other thing about him; &amp; when therin they had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied their deuotion, they vvould touch his body with their bookes, their beads, handkerchieffs, Croſſes, Medalles and other the like thinges, and that very reuerently on their knees: and in this kynde none were more forward then the Cardinalls themſelues; who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their more frequent conuerſation did beſt know him, and ſome of them mentioned his Canonization: &amp; when once they knew of his ſicknes they came very often vnto him, and ten of them ſomtymes in one day, who all deſired his bleſſing, but he conſtantly refuſed to giue it; and one of them taking him by the hand kiſſed the ſame, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touched his eyes and head therwith, at which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> meruayling when the other was gone asked thoſe about him, vvhat kind of curteſy this was, and how long it had beene in vſe amongſt the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls?</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19250:32"/>
                  <p>Another tyme the Cardinalls that came would needs before they departed kiſſe his hands, at which he was much<note place="margin">Great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence done him by Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls and Prelates.</note> grieued, and would haue withdrawne them backe, but was not able to reſiſt their importunity, and therefore only ſayd, <hi>non ſum dignus,</hi> I am not worthy of this honor eſpecially fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you my Lords, &amp; he offered to haue kiſſed theirs againe one by one, but they would not yield, &amp; he was to weake to force the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; ſome Cardinalls agayne togeather with other Prelats would needs haue his benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he vtterly refuſed to giue; &amp; they continuing to aske it, he craued theirs, ſo as the contention grew who ſhold bleſſe ech other; which a Cardinal perceauing decided the matter by taking <hi>Bellarmynes</hi> right hand, and bleſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe there with perforce, at which ſight the others not vvilling to vſe that violence, deſired agayne ſo earne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly his bleſſing on their knees, as he to auoyde ſo importunate moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giue it, but ſayd withall after he had giuen it: what will the bleſſing of a poore miſerable wretch as I am aualye you? why doe you trouble me ſo much
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19250:32"/> for it? And ſo in his death &amp; life the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours which with their ſweet ſtings do deadly wound others, he alwaies tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his greater humiliation.</p>
                  <p>Two Cardinalls aboue the reſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med<note place="margin">Cardinall Hippoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Aldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinus.</note> to be more ſollicitous of him, <hi>Aldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandino</hi> &amp; <hi>Farneſius;</hi> the firſt was then in <hi>Rome,</hi> the other abſent; the firſt came ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Nouitiate to enquire how he did, &amp; out of courteſy forbare to viſit him as not willing to trouble him with his preſence, yet at length he reſolued to ſee him, although his ſight coſt him teares; when he ſaw him paſt all hope of recouery, and meaſuring <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> by other men, he demaunded of F. <hi>Minutoli,</hi> vvhether the preſent apprehenſion of death did not affright him? Nothing leſſe, quoth the Father, of which your Honour ſhall now ſee the experience, and then asked the ſicke Cardinall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would not gladly depart to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other life. I would to God ſaid <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> that I might, and that very ſoone, I wiſh that I vvere already gone, for vvhat ſhould I ſtay any longer in this world? with other lik words which ſhewed not a deſire o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, but a delight alſo that he had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19250:33"/> to thinke on death; in ſo much as vvhen any would comfort him in his ſicknes, they would mention the ſame as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe moſt pleaſing vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Diuers wayes did this forſayd the Cardinall manifeſt his affection vnto <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> which I heere forbeare; and when he vvith others, requeſted that when he came to heauen, he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member<note place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſingular confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in God had great diſtruſt of himſelfe.</note> them, and pray for them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the vertuous Cardinall alwayes ſhewed a great hope and confidence in Gods mercy; yet vvas this conioyned with no leſſe diſtruſt of himſelfe, for he wold earneſtly craue euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s prayers, and to this petition of the Cardinalls he anſwered more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once ſaying: To go to heauen ſo ſoone is a great mater, &amp; to great for me; men vſe not to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch haſt, and for my ſelfe, I ſhall thinke it no ſmall fauour to be ſure of Purgatory, and there to remayne a good while in thoſe flames, that muſt purge and cleanſe the ſpotts of my offences, &amp; ſatisfy the iuſt wrath &amp; iuſtice of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God. But when I am come Home, quoth he, I will not faile to pray for you all; and this he promiſed to doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19250:33"/> for theſe Cardinalls, but for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactours &amp; ſeruants, vnto whom, &amp; to all thoſe in the Nouitiate he gaue (being thereunto much vrged) very often his bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>Cardinall <hi>Farneſius</hi> was at this tyme<note place="margin">Cardinall Farneſius his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and eſteeme of Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne.</note> at his houſe of <hi>Caprarola</hi> thirty miles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> who hearing of the ſicknes of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> wrote many letters to Father <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutoli,</hi> deſiring to be informed from time to tyme of the progreſſe of his ſicknes, and, when it ſhould happen, to haue the whole narration of his ſicknes and death togeather; moreouer that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> by him might be aduertiſed of the ſingular affection which he bare him, or as it pleaſed him to tearme it, <hi>dutifull reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">6. Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b.</note> adding withall: <hi>Mà quando piaceſſe à Dio, di voler questo Signore per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lo &amp;c.</hi> but in caſe it ſhould pleaſe God to call this Cardinall to heauen, I deſire your Fatherhood to procure me of F. <hi>Generall</hi> ſome payre of beades of the Cardinalls, or elſe his Breuiary, and I will make that account of it, as the great opinion I haue of his ſingular ſanctity doth require that I ſhould<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſame agayne he ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in another letter written foure
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19250:34"/> dayes after, at the end of which he added with his owne hand theſe wordes: <hi>Viuo con pena di queſta immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te perdita, mà inſieme</hi>
                     <note place="margin">10. Sept.</note> 
                     <hi>godo dell'opinione che gia ſi comi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cia ſcoprire della ſantità di queſto Signore.</hi> That is, I liue in paine of this loſſe ſo neere at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but withal I am glad for the opinion which already begins to manifeſt it ſelfe of the Sanctity of this honourable perſon. And in another which was written af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death he ſayth, that he will put<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9. Sept.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> before his eyes, <hi>come vn eſsempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re degniſsimo d'imitatione &amp;c.</hi> as an example moſt worthy of imitation: and I hope (ſayth he) not a little to be holpen by the interceſſion of that holy ſoule, that I may a far of follow his ſtepps, who hath ſo much honoured the whole Church &amp; ſacred Colledge of Cardinals, &amp; that no leſſe with his vertue then learning. So <hi>Farneſius,</hi> with more to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                  <p>This Cardinall in reſpect of the great obligation the whole Society hath euer had to that name, which his owne<note place="margin">Bellarmin did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteeme F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rneſius.</note> merits haue much more encreaſed, and for the particular affection he bare vnto <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> was of him alſo had in ſpeciall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19250:34"/> regard, &amp; as often as <hi>Farneſius</hi> his letters, ſtill full of loue, were read vnto him, he would in very effectuall wordes make remonſtrance how far he was indeared vnto him, &amp; how little able to diſcharge that duty which he did owe him, of which in his health he was neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myndfull, and had determined to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a great worke vnto him which he had began vpon S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning a literall, morall, and dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall explication of all the Apoſtles wordes; a worke worthy of <hi>Bellarmyne,</hi> neceſſary for theſe tymes, much vrged and deſired by many; but hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſome Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> conſidering with himſelfe the length and difficulty of the thing, his ſmall helpes, with other great imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his weake body, the ſhort and vncertayne tyme of his life, he left off that enterprize, &amp; wrote his other little bookes, as he inſinuateth in an epiſtle, to the Cardinal himſelf prefixed before his booke of <hi>The eternall felicity of Saints. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudo Operis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; breue ſpatium quod mihi ſupereſt vitae, &amp; quotidianae occupationes quae parùm omnino ad ſcribendum mihi otij re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linqunt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19250:35"/> effecerunt, vt de Opere illo perficiendo planè deſperarem:</hi> the length of the worke, the ſhort ſpace that remaynes of my life, and my daily buſines which leaues me very little leaſure to write, made me deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre of euer finiſhing that worke. So he: and for that it pleaſed Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> to ſhew ſuch ſingular gratitude to this his friend on his death-bed; &amp; on the other ſide, for that <hi>Farneſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> is further reſolued to erect ſome honourable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of him in the place where he is buried, I could not let him paſſe vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this narration.</p>
                  <p>And for the other Cardinalls, they<note place="margin">Bellarmin much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured &amp; loued of all the cardinals.</note> did alſo ſo tenderly affect him, as few or none of all thoſe which came to viſit him, could forbeare weeping: and one of them a very graue man ſayd vnto F. <hi>Minutol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> that he did greatly glory to hane been made Cardinall by that Pope which had made <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> Cardinall; and that <hi>in toto genere</hi> (I vſe his owne wordes) the world hath not had any of ſo ſingular learning accompanyed with ſo great humility and Religious maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as he, for many ages, &amp; perhaps may expect long ere it haue another. And
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19250:35"/> he did well to ſpecify his humility, for though he were equall to any, yet he ſo ſtil demeaned himſelfe as though he had beene ſeruant to all, and this euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till death; for to all that came vnto him in his ſicknes, although he did ſpeake with all reſpect and duty vnto them, yet at their departure he would craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them, and ſay; My Lords I pray pardon me, if I doe not as I would, or as I am bound, for I am not myne own man, I vvant ſtrength of body, I can do no more: and indeed he did more then was conuenient for one in his caſe to do, though much leſſe then he deſired to haue done to them, whom ſo hartily he did honour.</p>
                  <p>In fine, vvhen the danger of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe vvas once diuulged ouer all the Citty, not only Cardinalls, but many Biſhops, Prelates, and other of ſpeciall<note place="margin">Note the common opinion that all had of his ſanctity.</note> note repayred vnto him, eſpecially the three laſt dayes before his death, when being ſometymes ſleepy, ſometymes with his eyes cloſed in prayer and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he neyther marked vvho they were that came, nor heeded much what they did: in which tyme the foreſayd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19250:36"/> Cardinalls, Biſhops, Prelates and others ſent many little cappes of ſilke, ſuch as they vſe to were vnder their ſquare capps; and others ſent vvhite night-caps which they deſired might be put on his head as they were, and vvith them they ſent alſo little Croſſes of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Reliquiaries, prayer-bookes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges to touch him, and that in ſuch multitudes, as there vvere more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a hundred and fifty red, vvhite, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther capps put on, and taken from his head during this tyme, and ſince his death that number hath beene much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: many thinges vvere taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay by ſuch as came to viſit him, and thoſe alſo by great perſonages; many more vvere begged and ſought for from many places, as after in part I ſhall ſhew or rather touch only, for the particulars of this alone would much exceed the length of this Relation.</p>
                  <p>Honourable is vertue, and the root of all true honour, in regard vvherof the auncient Romans built the Temples of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> togeather, becauſe the one muſt neceſſarily depend of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as we ſee to haue hapned in this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19250:36"/> Cardinall whoſe vertues were conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous in the eyes and iudgement of all, as not only the good did deerely prize them and him for them, but alſo the bad did reuerence and honour them; in ſo much as hitherto I haue not heard of one in <hi>Rome</hi> that did not, and doth not honour him; yea the wicked Iewes ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes<note place="margin">Euen the Iewes did honour Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines vertues.</note> of all goodnes haue confeſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and (were their wordes of any weight) haue ſpoken of him in moſt honourable manner; in ſo much as a Prelate of great name ſayd, that <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> had ouercome all enuy and wonne the harts of all. And for that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſince his death haue ſo much extolled his vertues, I thinke it not amiſſe to let the Reader vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, what is now very opportunely come to my hands touching this point, out of <hi>Polonia,</hi> in a little booke written by a learned man of the Society of Ieſus vnder this title: <hi>Vindiciae doctrinae Societatis Ieſu, à calumnijs Patroni Turonenſium Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi. Auctore Georgio Tiſzkiewic,</hi> who rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a notable accident to this purpoſe which fell out vpon this occaſion.</p>
                  <p>There was ſet forth in print in the yeare 1614. a moſt infamous Libell, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19250:37"/> (as is thought) by ſome Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Heretike in Dutch of the the death<note place="margin">A notable teſtimony giuen of Bellarmin by a Iew in Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ia.</note> of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmyne,</hi> which related moſt ſtrange &amp; prodigious thinges of his life &amp; death: for <hi>Africk</hi> is not more full of monſters the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe men are of moſt mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous inuentions; amongſt other things it was reported that he dyed in the yeare 1613. when he was then aliue, &amp; wrote after that tyme all his ſpirituall bookes now in print. Beſids this, the whole Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell was ſo full of villany, as that many more moderate and modeſt Proteſtants diſclaymed in print from it, and none more vehemently then he who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue beene the printer, <hi>Lewis Coing</hi> dwelling in <hi>Baſil,</hi> a Citty of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> who wrote a ſharpe letter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the writer thereof, denying that euer he printed any booke, kept any preſſe, or had any thing to doe in ſetting forth of that Pamphlet; neuertheles the <hi>Caluinists</hi> in <hi>Dantz</hi> (a towne in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi>) reprinted the ſame againe, and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, as a great argument for the truth of their Ghoſpell, ſeeing that God had puniſhed the chiefe defendo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Faith of our Age with ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſtrous
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19250:37"/> and dreadfull death; and had he indeed beene dead, the lye though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo lowd had found credit amongſt the Brethren; but his life for ſo many yeares after quailed this fable; though yet ſome Merchants of more fayth then wit (for beſides their iuſtifying Fayth, they haue alſo an Hiſtoricall) did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirme and belieue it to be true; wherupon that fell out which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour aboue named doth report in theſe wordes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>Oliuae nonnulli Gedanenſium Senatorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alia quae ante annum vnum miſcebant cum admodum Reuerendo Patre Philippo Adlero digniſsimo Oliuenſis Monasterij Ordinis Sancti Bernardi Priore colloquia &amp;c.</hi> At <hi>Oliue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Conferences had between the chiefe Cittizens of <hi>Dantz,</hi> with the Reuerend Fa. <hi>Philip Adler</hi> Prior of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> they of <hi>Dantz</hi> related in one of them all thoſe thinges which the nameles Authour of the foreſayd Libell doth impudently report, or rather with which he doth moſt falſely calumniate the Cardinall. The Priour denyed all, affirming that they were impoſſible, &amp; out of the great good will and affection
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19250:38"/> he beares thereunto, did much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Society of Ieſus: on the other ſide they accuſed all, and aboue all <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmyne.</hi> Whiles they were in this debate, a Iew newly come out of <hi>Italy</hi> arryued thither, of which when the Prior was aduertiſed, he called for him to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and being come the Prior ſpake to him in this manner: haſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny newes from <hi>Rome</hi> to tell vs? what is become of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmyne?</hi> Is he aliue or dead? how, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth he liue? Heere our <hi>Dantz</hi> Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours ſtand attent, &amp; expect very gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily the anſwere, which they thought would ſecond their lewd reports; but contrarywiſe the Iew affirmed that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmyne</hi> was aliue, that he was in health, that his life for all vertue, grauity, and other deportment was moſt exemplar; that finally if the Iewes could ſee al Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, or the greater part, to liue as <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> doth, they would all of them preſently become Chriſtians. With this narration and their owne ſhame, the men of <hi>Dantz</hi> were not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. And this haue I heard from a moſt Religious and ſincere man, a Prior
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19250:38"/> alſo of the ſame Order, called <hi>Andrew Clewsky,</hi> who was both an eare, and eye witnes of this matter. Hitherto that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</q> So as now of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſanctity <hi>etiam inimici nostri ſint Iudices,</hi> the Iewes themſelues may be Iudges, who in this ſhevv themſelues to haue much more conſcience, then the forenamed Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes.</p>
                  <p>The deuotion of others vnto the Cardinall hath made me make the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger digreſſion from his owne perſon: but now leauing them a little (to whom eftſoones I ſhall returne againe) let vs a while contemplate, and caſt our eyes backe on the ſicke man, who perceauing in himſelfe ſo great decay of ſtrength, and his vitall ſpirits to be ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt, prayed more inſtantly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from this body of corruption, &amp;<note place="margin">His great deſire to be with God.</note> ſayd: Filthy fleſh only fit for wormes to feed on, why doeſt thou keep me from God? and taking the fleſh of one of his armes in his hand, he ſayd in Italian: <hi>Carnaccia traditora, perche non ſi stacchi? ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria pur tempo: che indugi? che stai à fare?</hi> Treacherous baſe fleſh, why doeſt thou not diſſolue and ſeuer thy ſelfe from the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19250:39"/> ſoule? it is high tyme: why doeſt thou delay? why doeſt thou not diſpatch and make an end? And then turning himſelfe vnto God, and wholy relying on his mercifull diſpoſition, he ſayd: <hi>non mea voluntas, ſed tua, fiat:</hi> not my will but thyne be done. And now drawing on apace to the laſt period of his life, he found more and more difficulty to take any meat, or keep what he had taken: and he had not only a great repugnance and auerſion from eating, but a great loathing and horrour to ſee any thing brought him. Heere what ſhould his attendants doe? to force him, ſeemed to violent for one ſo weake, ſo meeke, and of that ranke and dignity: to perſuade him, was but loſt labour, for ſuch diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultyes are hardly ouercome by perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: nothing remayned but to vrge him the Phiſitians commaund, and that he vvas bound vnder Obedience to<note place="margin">His exact obedience in thinges moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> eate.</p>
                  <p>Hereat preſently he would riſe, take and eate whatſoeuer they brought him, and that very readily though it were neuer ſo much agaynſt his ſtomacke, &amp; though he did preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly caſt it vp againe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19250:39"/> neuer looking or reſpecting what was giuen him: and which is more ſtrange, euen when he was beſides himſelfe in the extremity of his bad fit, the very name of Obedience would haue made him taken whatſoeuer they had brought him: ſo accuſtomed and affectioned he was to that Vertue, as nothing ſeemed hard vnto him, that came vnder that tytle, imitating therein his deere maiſter our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> witneſſeth: <hi>Ne perderet obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam, perdidit vitam,</hi> loſt his life that he might not looſe his obedience: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to that of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul: factus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>obediens vſque ad mortem,</hi> he was obedient euen vntill death. So Chriſt, ſo his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, &amp; I doubt not but that thoſe who ſhall write his life (if more then one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it) will fynd many notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of this vertue in the courſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <p>This here I wil auerre vpon certaine knowledge, that after his promotion, he put himſelfe vnder the Obedience of the <hi>Generall</hi> of his Order, and bound himſelfe to obey him no leſſe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all thinges of any moment. And
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19250:40"/> becauſe the Rules of the Society doe by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d all in the tyme of their ſicknes, not<note place="margin">When he was Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall he was obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Society, yea euen to his owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</note> only to obey the Phiſitians, but al ſuch as haue any care of them; the Cardinall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one of his chamber a moſt diligent and faythfull ſeruant to attend him in this ſicknes, him he alſo obeyed in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he bid him doe; and he knowing well his Lords pleaſure, when any thing was to be done, would not ſay as other ſeruants vſe to do, If it pleaſe your Honour to do this, or take that, and the like, but in reſolute tearmes: My Lord, lift vp your ſelfe, Take this, Doe that &amp;c. and preſently without any reply he would doe it, neuer ſaying more, but, As you will, As it pleaſeth you. Neither did this cuſtome begin betweene them on his death-bed, but had ſtill beene in vſe and practice before, and that with all humility and alacrity, for he regarded not whome he did obey, but for whoſe ſake he did it, and that made him euen in his ſeruants perſon to reuerence our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And ſo much for his Obedience.</p>
                  <p>The nynteenth day of his ſicknes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beginning of the new moone, his pulſe which hitherto had been ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19250:40"/> began much to fayle, and many other ill ſignes appeared which did euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticate his departure to be very neere at hand. The Cardinal ſtill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing as he could in his accuſtomed deuotions, in making deuout Colloquies, and iacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory prayers vnto God, when any thing was ſuggeſted vnto him fit for that tyme and preſent occaſion, he would thanke the ſuggeſtours, and giue them to knew<note place="margin">Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unted him a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> that he tooke great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort therof, which was in manner redoubled when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that the Pope had ſent him a Plenary Indulgence, for the better gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which ſpiritual grace he ſayd his <hi>Confiteor,</hi> with his diuers other prayers: &amp; the laſt night of his life which was the 23. of his ſicknes, the former ſignes ſtill continuing, and increaſing brought him into a certaine dulnes or inſenſibility, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſome fiue or ſix houres before his death, which made all who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him to thinke, that now euery houre might be his laſt: yet euen in this ſtate he made them all ſee, that he was preſent to himſelfe, knew his own dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, vnderſtood what was ſayd vnto him, and anſwered directly to whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19250:41"/> was propoſed: in ſo much as Father <hi>Minutoli</hi> ſpeaking vnto him of the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he was now to haue in God, and recourſe vnto his diuine mercy, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his help in this paſſage, for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of his ſinns, &amp; defence againſt all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the enemy now moſt vigilant; he anſwered very deuoutly &amp; directly vnto him in a low voice, that ſo he did, and that in the beſt manner he could, &amp; to manifeſt the ſame vnto them, to the end they might both ſee, that he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their wordes, and his owne caſe, he ſhewed this exteriour act of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an piety.</p>
                  <p>Hauing a little Croſſe of ſiluer in his hand, he kiſſed it very often, and<note place="margin">His great deuotion to the Croſſe.</note> bleſſed himſelfe diuers times wherwith, ſaying ſome prayers by himſelfe, ſome togeather with them that were with him, and kneeled at his bed ſide: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes taking into his hand a greater Croſſe that ſtood by which had the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our Sauiors body fixed theron, he did oftentimes very deuoutly kiſſe the the ſame; a little after he layed it on his eyes, and taking it from thence he layed it on his left ſhoulder, imbracing it very
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19250:41"/> hard between both his armes being put a croſſe one ouer the other, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a good while, till remouing it a little towards his breſt he lifted his hand vp to his head to take off his night-cap, but could not doe it, and ſuch as knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him knew not what he meant, til at laſt by coniecture Father <hi>Minutoli</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that he meant to doe ſome act of deuotion, and therfore tooke off his cap for him: then the Cardinall tooke the Croſſe, with both his hands, &amp; ſo much forced himſelfe, as he placed it on his bare head, and all this he did for the loue he bare to the death and paſſion of our Sauiour, whereof this Croſſe is a liuely repreſentation. Moreouer to ſhew the<note place="margin">Holy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</note> reuerence he bare vnto holy Images, for which point of Chriſtian beliefe more martirs haue loſt their liues by the hands of the bloudy &amp; barbarous Iconoclaſts, then perhaps they haue done for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther article whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I doubt not but that he ſhewed this zeale to the holy Crucifix, to ſhew his zeale againſt the Heretikes of theſe tymes, the true children of theſe parents and liuely brood of theſe Progenitours;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19250:42"/> that the world might ſee how exact he was in adhering vnto that Faith in all and euery branch and member which in his workes he had lo learnedly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and procured in this his laſt ſicknes as before I ſaid, to haue left regiſtred in print after his departure: Theſe reaſons I ſay, made him ſo often &amp; ſo earneſtly to exerciſe theſe acts of Veneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſſe; which finally he layed on his breſt vnder the couerlet where it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned till he was dead: ſo as he ſeemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſee, thinke or deſire any thing but Chriſt, and him crucifyed, and to teſtify to the world the interiour loue he bare in his hart to Chriſt, by the exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our reuerence which he did ſhew to his picture, the true character of a Catholike Chriſtian man.</p>
                  <p>Now was he come to the laſt houre of his life, and though his paines were<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his death.</note> greater, yet his courage, his patience, his quiet &amp; peaceable repoſe the ſame. The holy man began his prayers, ſayd the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter,</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> &amp; began againe the <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> which being ended he ſayd diſtinctly the Pſalme <hi>Miſerere,</hi> to the end: and being vvarned to ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19250:42"/> the Creed, in proteſtation of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and that he dyed a member of the Catholik, Apoſtolike &amp; Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church, preſently he began the ſame, and ſayd it all through, and (which was much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) with the end of the Creed he ended his ſpeach, theſe being the laſt wordes that euer he ſpake cleerly and diſtinctly<note place="margin">Vitam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam, Amen.</note> in this life: <hi>Et vitam aeternam, Amen:</hi> &amp; life life euerlaſting, <hi>Amen.</hi> After which his voice ſo fayled, that they could ſcant with all diligence vſed, heare him, yet he ſayd very ſoftly to himſelfe in ſuch manner as he was able Ieſus, Ieſus, Ieſus, and continued ſtill in the ſame till the laſt gaſpe, which of ſuch as beheld him was in a manner inſenſible, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny violent motion of his body or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting of his countenance, any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of his mouth, any panges or gaſps, in ſo ſtill, quiet, and peaceable faſhion as it ſeemed a ſleep rather then death, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a mylde and voluntary paſſage, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a matter of horrour or dread, rather a Saint-like repoſe then a finall departure out of this life. He left this world the ſeauenteeth day of September, betweene ſix and ſeauen of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19250:43"/> wanting not three weeks of three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and nynteene yeares, for he was borne on the fourth of October being <hi>S. Francis</hi> day, and dyed on the feaſt of the ſame Saint, dedicated to his ſacred woundes, which miraculouſly he had receaued; the ſolemnity of which feaſt the Cardinall much laboured with <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, to haue grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of that Order, with a ſpeciall Office for that day.</p>
                  <p>His body ſoone after his departure by a ſecret way, for auoyding the reſort of people, was conueyed in coach to the Church of the Fathers, where he was to<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion &amp; reuerence ſhewed to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> body.</note> be buried: &amp; becauſe as yet nothing was prepared for his expoſing, it was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed into a priuate chamber of the houſe with expreſſe order of debarring as yet all acceſſe vnto it: but there came ſo many to ſee and kiſſe the ſame, and ſo great perſonages, as the prohibition was ſoone recalled, and leaue graunted vnto moſt to come. All kneeled thereat as to the body of a Saint, and with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion kiſſed the ſame: ſome commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his learning, ſome his vertue, all his mylde, louing, and moſt affable beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19250:43"/> amongſt the reſt a great Prelate on his knees kiſſed the thumbe and two forefingers of his right hand, which had written ſo much to the glory of God, good of his Church, and comfort of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, no leſſe then fifty tymes: and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not inferiour to the former, did the ſame after him; which deuotion of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Prelates continued vntill it was an houre within night, and had done much longer, but that the Popes Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, togeather with his brother a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, came to open and enbalme the body, who earneſtly requeſted this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as a fauour at the Fathers hands, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they ſhould both of them grieue much in caſe any other ſhould do it.</p>
                  <p>As ſoone as they began the ſame, many were preſent with to wells, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchiffs,<note place="margin">He is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmed &amp; his bloud ſaued &amp; kept for reliques.</note> ſponges, and other linnen to ſaue the blod &amp; preſerue it for Reliques, and ſo Religiouſly induſtrious and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent they were, as nothing thereof was loſt: the Phiſitian himſelfe in lieu of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, cut away a little piece of the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of his which he eſteemeth as a peerles Iewell and ineſtimable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: the other three Phiſitians were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19250:44"/> prouided: for wheras in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his ſicknes they preſcribed that he ſhould be let bloud, &amp; another time to haue horſeleeches applyed to dravv more; at both of theſe tymes they came with cleane handkerchiffs, and dipped, or rather dyed them in the bloud, which by them and others was ſo greedily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as that no drop remayned; &amp; the Phiſitians were heerunto the more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for that beſides the common report and opinion of his vertue, they ſaw in this ſicknes ſuch liuely proofe therof, as none of them had euer ſeene the like in any before, which they neuer ceaſe to admire and commend whenſoeuer any mention is made, or occaſion giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake of his ſicknes.</p>
                  <p>The next morning the Nobility &amp; Gentry of the Congregation of our B. Lady got his body into their Oratory, or Chappell, where being all aſſembled they ſayd the Office of the dead for him, two Gentlemen alwayes ſtanding at his head to keep the multitude from kiſſing his beare face, permitting them only his handes and feet. He lay on a fayre hearſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, veſted like an Archbiſhop, with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19250:44"/> his myter and pall, in ſo gratious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as I neuer ſaw a fayrer corſe, and the ſame was ſayd by very many that ſaw him. The Office being ended, the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rownes of this place was not capable of ſo great concourſe, &amp; to auoid the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of ſuch preſſe of people, the more haſt was made to carry him into the Church, where being layd on a bed<note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of the people to his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Church.</note> prepared for the ſame, there came to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, or rather to reuerence and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it, as though, not the dead body of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> newly departed, but eyther the body of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> or S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> or ſome aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctour, Biſhop, or Patriarke had beene expoſed and layed open to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured: and I know not what more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion the people could haue vſed vnto their ſacred reliques, then now they did vnto the body of this Cardinall.</p>
                  <p>For they came not as ordinarily on ſuch occaſions they vſe to doe, to gaze, &amp; ſee the pompe of the funeralls (which heere was very litle) not to pray for the party deceaſed, not to enquire of his heires, his teſtament, his wealth, his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, or the like more curious then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19250:45"/> matters; but to ſee as they called him, the Saint, to pray vnto him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence his body, and that in ſuch ſort, as if already he had beene canonized: &amp; for that it was now placed higher then they were able to reach, and compaſſed by ſome of the Popes Guard, and Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers of the Cardinals that came to be preſent at the <hi>Dirige,</hi> they wearyed them all with giuing their beades vnto them, which the one on the top of their trun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheons, the other of their Maſſes, lifted vp to touch his bare face; and ſo many beades being giuen to touch, and that ſo continually without any intermiſſion, all looked or rather feared that his face would haue been disfigured therewith, for it was touched, as moſt coniecture by more then twenty thouſand payre of beades; and there had beene no end of touching it, had not the Fathers with help of the Popes Guarde after more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three houres within night caryed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way perforce, as preſently ſhall be ſaid: and notwithſtanding that the body lay aloft, was well guarded with tronche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and halbardes, yet were there of theſe pious theeues ſo cunning, as that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19250:45"/> ſome of them cut away pieces of his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">Great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to get reliques of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> that he wore, others the taſſells and knots of his Cardinalls hat, others the skirts of his veſtements, others other things; &amp; what ech could get with great deuotion he kiſſed the ſame, lapping it vp in cleane linnen, ſilke &amp;c. and two Prelates brought ech a ſhort ſtaff vnder his garment, and when they came ouer againſt one the other at the lower end of the hearſe, where the hat lay at the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls feet, they caſt it off from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dexterouſly with their ſtaues into the boſome of one of their ſeruaunts ready at hand to receaue it, who had conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it cleane away, had not one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by chance eſpyed him, who by help of the Pops Guard recouered it out of his hands, and carryed it into the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. In fine had not his body beene well guarded, I thinke that neyther hat, or myter, or veſtement, or any thing elſe had beene left, and perhaps the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it ſelfe had been taken away &amp; deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for pious ſpoile.</p>
                  <p>And although his body were thus expoſed in more plaine and poſitiue manner, with leſſe ſplendour and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19250:46"/> then is accuſtomed for Cardinalls:<note place="margin">Great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Cardinals to his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.</note> yet were his Exequies in other reſpectes very honourable. For contrary to that which both in his wil he had deſigned, &amp; deſired of the Generall on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to haue no Cardinals preſent ther at, there came ſo many as more haue not beene ſeene at any buriall: for excepting two or three for exceeding g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat age, ſicknes, or ſome other buſines abſent, all the reſt were there, and ſtayed vntill the very end of the office, which was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the General in his Cope, and the Fathers of the Society: and further there was ſuch reſort as none liuing euer ſaw more, or perhaps ſo many at once in that Church. When the Office was done, to ſatisfy the importunate requeſt of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as deſired it, the body was taken downe, layed on a Beare couered with blacke veluet, and caryed to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of our Bleſſed Lady in the ſame Church, not without a ſtrong Guard, where ſuch as entred at one dore paſſing out at an other gaue way for more to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy their deſires; but it was not poſſible to ſatisfy all; for though it remayned there vntill after three houres in the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19250:46"/> night (as I ſayd) yet were the Fathers forced to ſend away many that were ſtil flocking thither much agaynſt their wil, and not without mayne force of the Guard and others, that commaunded &amp; compelled them out of the Church, and ſhut the dores, to their no ſmall regreet.</p>
                  <p>The multitude being excluded, the body was put into a plaine coffin of wood, and layed in the ordinary vault<note place="margin">He is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in a common vault.</note> where others of the Society are wont to be buryed: therein condeſcending to the Cardinalls deſire, who would needes lye with them in graue, with whome he had liued, whome he had loued, and to whome for many years before his death he would haue returned, and ledd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne a Religious life, vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Rule, vvith the reſignation of his Cardinalls Hat and dignity, if it might haue been permitted him, as I haue been informed by one to whome he impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his mynd, and would haue vſed in the ſame; and my ſelfe haue heard him very hartily to wiſh it. But howſoeuer for ſome ſmall tyme (for long as I heare it ſhall not remayne in that place) his body reſt in a poore vault, yet his ſoule
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:19250:47"/> yet vvere his other noble vertues ſo ſhrowded vnder the mantle of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; as they could not be ſeene in their perfect nature; and ſuch as beſt knevv them, had leaſt liſt to ſpeake them, leſt them vvordes might diſcloſe vvhat the Cardinall vvould haue to be ſecret: but novv hath that Glory ouertaken him vvhich he did ſtill eſchew, &amp; beat backe vvith contempt of himſelfe; novv he vvho ſeemed amongſt the Cardinalls to be inferiour to all, is more honoured then any: novv that the earthen pot of his mortall body is broken, the ſhyning lamp of his vertues accompanyed vvith the trump and triumph of fame, yield their light to the vvorld, &amp; conſound all malitious inuentions of the <hi>Mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites.</hi> Novv is the candle no more layed<note place="margin">Iud. 7.</note> vnder a buſhell, but ſet on a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke for all to behold: novv is the mouth of detractors ſtopped that would vvith their lyes haue blemiſhed his life, and diſgraced his death many yeares ere it hapned: novv (vvill they, nill they) truth ſhall trample falſhood vnderfoot, and the cleere beames of <hi>Bellarmynes</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ouerbeare all ſlaunderous reports of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19250:47"/> malignant Sacramentaryes. Let them forge infamous fictions, let them print as they haue done moſt exorbitantlyes, let malice ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cht with learning, arme their pennes to write reproach, yet ſhall all their force and fury fal to the ground, &amp; his name be renowned for euer. The warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ſure that is ſigned with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, who ſayd by the Pſalmiſt: <hi>In me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a erit iustus, ab auditionemal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 111.</note> 
                     <hi>timebit:</hi> the memory of the iuſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne for euer, he ſhall not feare any ill report: and not only his life and death, but as the Prophet foretold of Chriſt, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſepulerum eius glorioſum,</hi> euen his ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſhall be glorious; for thither now<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.</note> come many to pray, thereon dayly they caſt freſh flowers, thereof they ſpeake, that ſpecially they reſpect: it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before to many, but is now made famous by him alone.</p>
                  <p>The Habit, as the Philoſopher ſayth, is beſt knowne by his Priuation; the darke night makes vs more to eſteem and valew the cleere day, and liberty is alwayes moſt gratefull after a long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint: ſo <hi>Bellarmines</hi> abſence hath made his vertues more prized, and the ſenſe &amp;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19250:48"/> feeling which now all find in his want, makes them vvith griefe to recall to mynde, what a treaſure they had whiles they did enioy him aliue. The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals haue loſt the prime flower &amp; brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtarre of their Colledge, the Biſhops a liuely patterne of a true Paſtour; the Religious a perfect example of imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the learned a renowned Docto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r; the poore a Father; the afflicted a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter; the whole Church an ornament; and to renew ſtill his happy memory in their neuer dying affection, many Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls, Prelates and others of great No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility haue carefully ſought, and alwaies do ſeeke for ſomething of his; and ſo much is already gotten, as beſides his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy little or nothing elſe is left. One Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall got his bed, another his Miſſall, another his Diurnall, <hi>Farneſius</hi> his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iary. What others got eyther during his ſicknes or ſince his death were to long to write; they got his dublet, hoſe, ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, caps, linnen, wollen, writings, pictures, ſhirts, handkerchiffs; and what elſe they could procure, leauing him ſo deſtitute of all thinges, as that the Fathers of the Society were forced
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19250:48"/> after his death to cloath him of their owne, and to borrow a ſquare cap of an other Cardinall to put on his head (whiles his body for a day and night lay in a lower chamber at the <hi>Caſa Proſeſsa</hi>) his clothes and caps being eyther all ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or giuen away before.</p>
                  <p>And not in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rome only, but from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">His Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by many.</note> places abroad many letters haue beene ſent, and meanes vſed to get ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing that had beene his, which I let paſſe, ſetting downe only the clauſe of one letter written by a very worſhipfull Gentleman of our owne Nation, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in <hi>Naples,</hi> which came to my hands as I was writing this Relation. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wrote it in Italian, that the Generall (to whome he is well knowne) might ſee it, &amp; in this manner. <hi>Son stato agrauato &amp; questo con grandiſsima inſtanza della Sig<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Ducheſsa di Santo Elia molto mia Signora, &amp; Patrona, di ſarli hauere qualche coſa che ſoſse della felice memoria dell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Illuſtriſsimo Sig<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinale Bellarmino; come a dire, qualche beret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tino di tela che ildetto haueſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e portato, o qualche parte di vua ſua camiſia, e questo per la gran diuotione, che la detta Signora porta al morto: &amp; eſsendo biſogno, pregarà N. N. in nome mio
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19250:49"/> di cooperare quanto ſia poſsibile, di trouar qualche coſa per conſolare la diuotione di questa Signora.</hi> That is: I haue beene vrged, &amp; that with exceeding importunity by the Dutches of S. <hi>Elias,</hi> my very good Lady and Patroneſſe, to procure herſom what of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; that is to ſay, ſome linnen night-cap which he hath worne, or ſome piece of his ſhirt, and this for the great deuotion the ſayd Lady beares towardes the dead Cardinall. And if need be, you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate N. N. in my name to help as much as is poſſible to find out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to comfort the deuotion of this Lady. So he. And although that this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came ſoone after his death, yet were all theſe things eyther giuen, or taken, or ſtolne away ere it came, &amp; her requeſt ſatisfyed another way.<note place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In fine, no man in Rome of his ranke in the memory of any man liuing hath dyed with ſo generall good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all; no funeralls haue beene cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated with ſo great concourſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; no ſepulcher ſo much frequented<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Two and twenty yeares he liued Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall; fourty a Religious man; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19250:49"/> betyme to beare the yoke of Chriſt; was neuer wearyed; neuer ſainted till the end. A man of ſuch lenity and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as he would offend none; of ſuch candour and ſincerity, as he could not diſſemble with any; of ſuch kindnes &amp; courteſy, as he was beneuolous vnto all. Of temporall emoluments he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer moued with loſſe, or delighted with increaſe; his wealth was the poore mans gaine, not his owne profit; his loſſe their hinderance, not his hurt; to men of our Iland as wel Engliſh and Scottiſh he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſhewed himſelfe a worthy friend and ſpeciall benefactour; neuer denying them any thing that conueniently he could graunt; neuer ſparing his labour, his pen, or purſe to pleaſure them as far foorth as he was able; of which I could alleadge very many examples, were not that field to large, and this no place to recount them. Of all which, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe he did, we may now ſay, <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um in portis opera eius,</hi> his workes praiſe him in the gates; that is, at the tribunall and Iudgement ſeat of God, where their worth is valued, and their valour rewarded, and he in his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19250:50"/> revvardes glorious for all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                  <p>Heere if any out of a curious mynd, ſhould expect to heare ſomwhat ſpoken of ſome miraculous euent which hath<note place="margin">Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſanctity is ſingular there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no miracles to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme it.</note> hapned in, or ſince his death, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmation of his ſincerity: I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were hereunto, that as the ſanctity of S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did ſufficiently warrant it ſelfe without any miracle at all, beſides his miraculous vertues: ſo the happy life and death of this Cardinal being ſuch as they were, need no other miracles then the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for their proofe. And to ſpeake o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly of his death, what was his inuincible patience without the leaſt ſigne of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or ſillable of complaint? what his ſecurity of mynd ouerbearing all tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? what his purity of conſcience vvithout all mortall remorſe? vvhat his exact Obedience without reply? vvhat his reuerent receauing of the Bleſſed Sacrament, his conſtancy in faith, his deuout death, but a miracle, or rather many miracles in one? Who can eſteeme othervviſe of his courage agaynſt death novv looking him in the face, when he deſired it to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19250:50"/> draw neerer, to take him away, then that it was miraculous? Vnles he will contradict the iudgement of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who writing of his brother <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ds</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bernard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. in Cant.</note> death, hath theſe wordes: <hi>Acci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s ſum ad id miraculi, videre exult ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, inſultantem morti.</hi> I was called to that miracle, to ſee a man reioying in death triumphing ouer death. Truly this holy Cardinall, as you haue heard, ſo much reioyced in death, as he had no other ſorrow in his ſicknes, then to thinke that it was further from him, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was, or greater ioy, then when he was to ſhake handes with it; the true effect of a well prepared mynd, for as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth: <hi>mortem venientem nemo hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>excipit niſi qui ſe ad illam diu compoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t:</hi> no man cheerfully imbraceth death, but he that hath long before prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for it.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things, I ſay, need no other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle then themſelues to confirme them. For at <hi>S. Aug.</hi> ſaith of ſuch a one as wold foure hundred years after Chriſt ſee ſome<note place="margin">Aug. l. 22. de Ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. Dei cap. 8. initio.</note> miracle that he might belieue: <hi>Magnum ipſe prodigi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m eſt, qui mundo credeme prodigia adhuc inquiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vt credat:</hi> he is himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19250:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:19250:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:19250:52"/> who ſeeing the world to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in Chriſt, doth yet ſeeke for ſome miraculous wonder to belieue: So in<note place="margin">The ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of Bellarmin very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all that knewe him.</note> this caſe, ſeeing the former miracles, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common opinion that all haue of his Holines, ſeing all that euer knew him, to haue canonized him with deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his body, or conſtant report of his integrity; ſeeing all his writinges to haue beene to confound hereſy, to erect the banner of truth, to comfort the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to teach the ignorant, to aduance vertue; ſeeing all his actions to haue beene ſigned with innocency, to haue proceeded from charity, and by pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to haue beene directed to Gods glory or good of his neighbour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touch, ſpot, or reprehenſion in the vvhole courſe of his life; he may indeed be thought prodigious that would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeke any other confirmation, any other miracle, or miraculous proofe; which I doe not ſay to condemne or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way extenuate the force of other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, God forbid, for ſomtymes they are neceſſary, &amp; heere they are not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: but only to ſhew that eminent ſanctity may proue it ſelfe by the cleere
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19250:52"/> beames of her owne beauty, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any borrowed light deriued from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall power, as it did in S. <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> aboue mentioned, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints.</p>
                  <p>YET for further confirmation of this<note place="margin">The time of Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed &amp; foretold to Pope Gregory the xv.</note> particular, ther are ſomethings reported, &amp; not reported o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly but manifeſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aculous. Or which that firſt occurreth to be remembred, that the Generall, after the death and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uneralls of the Cardinall repayring for audience to this preſent Pope, Gregory the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, was willed by the ſayd Pope to read a letter which he tooke from of a little table and gaue him, in reading wherof, he found theſe wordes: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſixtenth and ſeauententh of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Cardinall Bellarmyne shall go to heauen,</hi> and as his Holines teſtified the writer of that letter, could not then when he wrote it, ſo much as haue heard of the Cardinalls ſicknes: and indeed about midnight of the ſixteenth day he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his agony, and dyed the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Although out of humility the Writer deſired to haue his name concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; yet doth the thing it ſelfe ſpeake
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19250:53"/> both <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſanctity, and thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py end, and the ſingular vertue of the ſaid party, and great vnion with God: for he could not haue knowne this but by reuelation, no naturall cauſes to one ſo far abſent, being able to yield ſo exact &amp; punctuall aſſurance in ſo vncertayne a caſuality as is the life of man, which dependeth on ſo many, and thoſe ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinate circumſtances, as are the meanes by which it may be eyther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and cut off, or elſe drawne on to a greater length. This knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone appertayneth vnto him, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing can lye hid, &amp; in whoſe hands alone are all our liues, all momentes, all tymes, which by vs can be no more or leſſe knowne, then it ſhall pleaſe his mercifull Goodnes to open and diſcloſe vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>The ſame morning that the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall departed this life, his voyce was<note place="margin">He reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his owne happines.</note> heard to ſpeake vnto ſome in the Citty (of the number I am vncertayne) and to ſay vnto them, <hi>Adio, adeſso me ne vado in Paradiſo:</hi> farewell, for euen now I go to heauen: which voyce amongſt others was heard of the Dutches of <hi>Sforza,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19250:53"/> vertuous Lady now liuing in Rome: and one of the other who heard the like voice did not at that time know that the Cardinall was in any danger of death at all. The Vertue, Nobility, multitude of theſe perſonages, togeather with the vniforme report, is a ſufficient warrant of their words. And euen now (though ſomwhat late) is come to my handes a briefe Relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a miraculous cure done by a Relique of his, vpon a Religious woman of the order of S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> called <hi>Paula Landi,</hi> in the Monaſtery of our B. Ladyes in <hi>Campo Martio</hi> of Rome. Thus the thing fell out.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid <hi>Paula</hi> the ſixth day of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<note place="margin">A ſtrange and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous cure done by a Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lique o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> by a fall brake one of her rib-bones in ſuch ſort, as that one part thereof did ſtand out, and the other was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards her breſt; the paine ſhe felt was exceſſiue, and withall her weaknes was ſuch, as ſhe could not veſt herſelfe, eate, or vſe her arme. The Surgeon in ſetting the bone right, increaſed her paine; and beſides the extremity of her bodily griefe, ſhe was in wardly alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much afflicted in mynde with the feare eyther of a continuall lamenes if
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19250:54"/> ſhe did recouer, or with the long end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance of that inſupportable torment which would haue no other end, then the end of her life. Whiles ſhe remayned in the perplexity of theſe afflicting thoughts, there was brought to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery a piece of linnen, that had tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Cardinalls body, which ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to haue, &amp; when ſhe had it, did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſame to the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d much ſwolne with the concourſe of humors: then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking herſelfe to prayer, hartily craued the interceſſion of the holy Cardinall; &amp; loe in the ſpace of one houre ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all paine, could veſt herſelfe, walke, and doe any thing as before, in ſo much as on the Sonday following (for this hapned on fryday) ſhe ſerued the reſt at table, and at this preſent is as well able to doe any thing as euer ſhe was before. And this the party hath te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed to my ſelfe, who purpoſely got leaue to ſpeake with her about this matter; and not only the ſayd <hi>Paula,</hi> but others of her Order, who were preſent when I ſpeake vnto her, did teſtify th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſame, adding further that all of the ſayd Monaſtery would doe the like; &amp; <hi>Paula</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19250:54"/> herſelfe wrote as much as here I report, ſubſcribed the ſame with her own hand, and ſent it to the Fathers of the Society of the <hi>Caſa Profeſsa,</hi> where the Cardirall is buryed.</p>
                  <p>Since the former cure there hath hapned another, &amp; that vpon an Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonage, to wit, the Lord <hi>Riui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ullo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bel-Caſtro.</hi> This man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much afflicted with a payne in his ſides, that wonderfully moleſted him, before he vvould apply any medicine thereunto, called for a little red cap of ſilke, which <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> did vveare vnder his ſquare cap, and confiding much in his merits and interceſſion, touched thoſe partes that grieued him therewith, and incontinently he was cured, and fully deliuered from all payne, as the ſaid Honourable Perſonage hath teſtifyed and confirmed by his Oath, Hand, and Seale. More in this kind I might write; but for that I haue not ſuch meanes to ſearch out their truth, as I thinke is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, ere they be thus diuulged, I leaue them to others to relate, who doe better know them: and in the hiſtory of his life which already is thought vpon
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19250:55"/> they will I doubt not be moſt faithfully recorded, to the Glory of God, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Seruant, and Comfort of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Theſe thinges thus teſtifyed, I thought good to ſet downe, which haue ſo ſoone hapned after his death, becauſe in part they confirme vvhat before I wrote of his holy life and ſaint-like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture. God graunt vs his Grace ſo to imitate his Vertues, as we may ſhut vp this our mortall and fraile life, with ſo happy an end. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>Cardinall <hi>Bellarmyne</hi> was borne in the yeare 1542. the fourth day of October being the feaſt of S. <hi>Francis.</hi> He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Society of Ieſus at Rome the 20. day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember 1560. He vvas made Cardinall the third day of March 1599. he dyed in the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19250:55"/> Nouitiate of Rome the 17. of September 1621. being fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and the feſtiuall day of the holy vvoundes miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly imprinted in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, feet, and ſide of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> 24. dayes after he had left the Court, vvanting but ſixteene dayes of threeſcore and nyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares of age. He liued in the Society before his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion 38. yeares, fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and thirteene dayes; in his Cardinalate two and twenty yeares, ſix moneths, and fourteene dayes: <hi>Cuius memoria in benedictionibus dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="will">
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19250:56"/>
                     <head>Exemplar Teſtamenti Illuſtriſsimi Carainalis Bellarmini.</head>
                     <p>IN nomine Domini Ieſu Chriſti. Ego Robertus Bellarminus Tit. Sanctae Mariae in Via P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>esbyter Cardinalis ex Societate Ieſu aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, petij à Sanctae memoriae Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Viij. facultatem condendi Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad pias cauſas tantùm, vt certus eſſem ea quae mihi decedenti bona temporalia ſupereſſent, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue dum viuerem diſpenſari Paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, vel Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s non potuerant, vtpote meae ſuſtentationi neceſſaria, ad Pauperes, &amp; Eccleſias redirent; conceſſit Pontifex indultum Teſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di general<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us quàm voluiſſem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed non acceptaui, niſi ad pias cauſas, vt petieram. Habetur hoc indultum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alias Bullas mihi conceſſas, in mag no folio pergameno cum plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, datum anno Domini 1603. ſex to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19250:56"/> Idus Aprilis, Pontificatus Sanctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Papae Clementis Viij. anno 12. Ergo hoc indulto prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uppoſito Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentum condi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i Capuae cùm eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Achiepiſcopus eius Ciuitatis deinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o abrogato aliud condidi Romae, ſed propter circumſtantias mutatas, hoc ſecundo etiam abrogato, nunc ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Teſtamentum condere ſtatui, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſim annorum ſoxaginta nouem, &amp; proximus vltimae diei, vt opinor, ſed ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; corpore per Dei gratiam bene valens. Primùm igitur ſpiritum meum in manus Dei commendatum toto corde exopto, cui ab Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia ſeruire deſideraui, &amp; precor, vt me inter Sanctos &amp; Electos ſuos non aeſtimator meriti, ſed veniae lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitor admittat. Corpus meum, non apertum, nocturno tempore ſine vlla pompa ad Eccleſiam Societatis Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, vel Collegij Romani, vel Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Profeſſae deferri volo. Et exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiae fiant per ſolos Patres &amp; Fratres
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19250:57"/> Societatis, ſine interuentu ſacri Col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legij, ſine lecto ſublimi, ſine inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijs, vel flabellis, eademue ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, quae ceteris de Societate fieri <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>olent. Et hac de re, quàm maxime poſſum ſanctiſſimum Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum humiliter rogo, vt deſiderio meo ſatisfaciat. Quod attinet ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ſepulturae, libenter iacere corpus meum voluiſſem ad pedes B. Aloyſij Gonzagae, mei quondam ſpiritualis filij, ſed tamen Superiores Societatis vbi voluerint, corpus meum ponant. De rebus temporalibus mihi à Sede Apoſtolica co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſſis, vel vndecum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> acquiſitis ita diſpono. Haeredem v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſalem nomino, &amp; inſtituo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum profeſſam Romanam Societa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Ieſu, in qua religione nomen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Volo au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt primò ſoluantur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita ſi quae fuerint, &amp; iura ijs quibus debentur. Deinde dentur familiae ad quadraginta dies more ſolito, quae ad victum pertinent, id eſt quod illis
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19250:57"/> taxatum eſt in pecunia propane, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o, &amp; companatico. Neque aliud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is relinquere poſſum, cùm ad ſolas pias cauſas Teſtamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faciendi fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatem petierim: &amp; eadem cauſa ſingulis ſtipendium ſiue prouiſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aliquam dederim, praeter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. Fratri meo ſecundum carne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, vel eius Haeredibus, reſtituatur I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mago, ſeu quadrum Clementis viij. Pontificis maximi. Nepoti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eo An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo, detur Imago, ſeu quadrum Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berti Card. de Nobilibus, &amp; vnum ex duobus quadris S. Caroli Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romaei, &amp; vna ex paruis Crucibus quas ad pectus gero cum reliquijs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſis. Collegio Romano reſtitua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur Annalium Card. Baronij tomi ſex, quos mihi acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modauit, vt eide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur alij ſex mei, nam cùm hac co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one accepi à Coll. ſex primos tomos qui me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> nomine dati fuerunt Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio eidem ab eodem Auctore, vt poſt obitum relinquerem integru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opus.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19250:58"/> Eidem Coll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> relinquo vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex tribus Planetis pretioſis cum ſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo, quam vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erit, &amp; omnia ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mea, &amp; totum Bibliothecam, niſi Reuerendiſſimo Patri Generali vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur Bibliotheca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alicui alteri loco Societatis magis egenti applicare. Sanctae Mariae in Via, qui titul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt, relinquo vnam ex tribus Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netis pretioſis, quam haeres meus da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re voluerit. Aliud titulo meo non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquo, quoniam ſatis multùm ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendi in fabrica Eccleſiae, vt Fratres ſciunt, qui hoc ipſum petierunt loco paramentorum, quae illis emere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitueram. Reliqua omnia bona quae quocumque modo ad me pertinent, ſeu pertinebunt, ſiue immobilia, ſiue mobilia, ſiue ſe mouentia, ſiue iura, ſiue credita, ſiue ſacra ad Cappellam ſiue profana ad veſtiarium, vel cellas varias pertinentia, ſiue pecunias nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meratas, ſiue quaecumque alia, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra ad haeredem, id eſt ad Domum
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19250:58"/> Profeſſam Romanam Societatis Ieſu vt dictum eſt pertineant, volo; &amp; in illis omnibus, &amp; ſingulis ipſam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redem inſtituo, &amp; nomino. Pro au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilio Animae meae nihil relinquo, vel preſcribo, quia parùm admodum erit, quod ad Haeredem meum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniet vt exiſtimo, cùm ego cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landis pecunijs, vel rebus pretioſis acquire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis numquam ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim; tum quia confido, imo certò ſcio no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defuturam huic officio piam charitatem Matris meae, Religionis videlicet Societa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is Ieſu, vt pro alijs filijs ſuis numqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> deeſt, &amp; quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ego non deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u toto vitae meae tempore pro defunctis Societatis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificia, &amp; orationes Deo oſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. Executorem hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s meae voluntatis nomino honoris cauſa Illuſtriſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Reuerendiſſimum Dominum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Cardinalem Aldobrandinum: la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor enim, vt exiſtimo, nullus erit in executione Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti huius. Relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19250:59"/> aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em Illuſtriſſimo Domino meo id quod pretioſius nihil habeo, videlicet Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cem ligneam reliquijs pretioſiſſimis refertam, quarum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogus in ſcriniolo cooperto holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerico rubro inuenietur.</p>
                     <p>Hoc Teſtamentum valere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo prioribus abrogatis, quae in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; per omnia reuoco, caſſo, &amp; annullo, etiamſi hoc forte non fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit cum debi tisſolemnitatibus factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. id enim apertè concedit Bulla Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Pontificis Clementis viij. in qua mihi data eſt facultas teſtandi, etiam per ſimplicem epiſtolam, vel ſcedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam manu mea ſubſcriptam.</p>
                     <p>Ego Robertus Cardinalis Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larminus vt ſupra diſpono, inſtituo, lego, &amp; reſtor, non ſolùm praefato, ſed omni meliori modo. Die 23. Ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arij 1611.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:19250:59"/>
                     <head>A Copy of the last Wil and Teſtament of Cardinall Bellarmyne, made in the yeare 1611.</head>
                     <p>IN the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. I Robert Bellarmyne Cardinall of the tytle of our Bleſſed Ladyes Church called <note n="*" place="margin">This tytle was changed a yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, and he made titular of S P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> in Via, being promoted therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to out of the Society of Ieſus, deſired leaue of Clement the 8. of holy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to mak my wil that my goods might be applyed to pious vſes, that I might be ſure that ſuch temporall thinges as ſhould remayne after my death, &amp; ſuch as vvhiles I liued, could neyther be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on the poore or on Churches, as being neceſſary for myne own maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, might returne vnto the ſaid poore and Churches.</p>
                     <p>The Pope gaue me a more generall graunt then I deſired, which I did not accept, but only for beſtowing them on good vſes as I had deſired. This Indult or graunt is amongſt other Bulls graunted me, in a great leafe of Parchment ſealed with lead, dated in the yeare 1603. the 8. day of Aprill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 12. yeare of the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19250:60"/> of the ſayd Pope Clement.</p>
                     <p>This graunt preſuppoſed, I made my will at Capua whiles I was Archbiſhop of that Citty: afterwardes that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing annulled I made another in Rome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the circumſtances of thinges being altered, and that ſecond alſo abrogated, I determyned now agayne to make my will, being of the age of threeſcore and nyne, and very nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e as I imagine to my laſt day, but yet by the grace of God in perfect health of body &amp; mynd.</p>
                     <p>Firſt therfore I deſire with all my hart, to haue my ſoule commended into the hands of God, whome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my youth I haue deſired to ſerue; and I beſeech him, not as the valewer of merit, but as a giuer of pardon, to admit me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Saints and Elect.</p>
                     <p>I will haue my body, not being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, to be caryed without any pompe to the Church of the Society, eyther of the Roman Colledge, or of the profeſſed Fathers: and let the exequies be made by the Fathers and brothers alone of the Society, without concourſe of the holy College (to wit of the Cardinalls) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any bed made aloſt, without armes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19250:60"/> or ſcutcheons, with the ſame playnenes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is accuſtomed for others of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and in this I doe as earneſtly as I can humbly entreat his Holines that he will ſatisfy my deſire,</p>
                     <p>As for the place of my buriall, I would gladly haue had my body layen at the feet of Bleſſed <hi>Aloyſius Gonzaga</hi> once my ghoſtly child, but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, let the Superiours of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety bury it where they liſt.</p>
                     <p>Of the temporall thinges graunted me by the Sea Apoſtolike, or gotten any<note place="margin">To the profeſſed Fathers.</note> other way, I diſpoſe in this manner. I nominate and make my generall Heire the houſe of the Profeſſed Fathers in Rome of the Society of Ieſus, of which Order I was; but firſt of al I wil that my debts be payed if there be any, and all dutyes diſcharged to vvhome they are due: then for fourty dayes (as is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion) let there be giuen to my family ſuch thinges as appertayne vnto their diet, that is to ſay, ſo much as is allotted them in money for their bread, wyne, and victualls. I am able to leaue them nothing elſe, becauſe I deſired this leaue of making my will, to beſtow all I had
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19250:61"/> on pious vſes (as Churches and poore people) and for that cauſe gaue euery one of them wages, or ſome allowance beſides their die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>Let there be reſtored vnto myne<note place="margin">To his brother &amp; Kinſman.</note> own brother, or to his heires, an Image in a frame, of Pope Clement the 8. Let there be giuen to my nephew <hi>Angelo</hi> alſo a little picture, in a frame, of <hi>Robert</hi> Cardinall <hi>de Nobilibus,</hi> and one of the two, in frames, of S. <hi>Charles Borromaeus.</hi> and one of the little Croſſes vvhich I weare about my neck with the reliques that are in it.<note place="margin">To the Roman Colledge.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let there be reſtored to the Roman College ſix tomes of the Annales of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius which it lent me, that other ſix of myne might be giuen to the ſame: for on this condition I receaued of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the firſt ſix tomes which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thereunto in my name by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour himſelfe, that after my death I ſhould leaue them all his vvorkes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiere.</p>
                     <p>To the ſame Colledge I leaue one of my three beſt veſtments with the ſtole and manuple, which it pleaſeth, alſo all my writings, &amp; my whole library, vnles
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19250:61"/> it ſhal pleaſe our moſt Reuerend Father Generall to beſtow the library on ſome other Houſe of the Society, that is more in need.</p>
                     <p>To our Bleſſed Ladyes Church <hi>in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">To his firſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Via,</hi> which is my titular, I leaue another of my three beſt veſtments, ſuch as it ſhal pleaſe myne Heyre to giue. I leaue no more to that Church, becauſe as the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars know I haue beene at great charge in building of the ſame; and they reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted that of me in lieu of other Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which I had determined to haue bought them.</p>
                     <p>Whatſoeuer elſe doth belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto me, or ſhall belong, whether immoueables, moueables, liuing thinges, whether du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes or debts owing me, whether ſacred belonging to my Chappell, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane belonging to my wardrobe, or to my cellars, or other places, whether rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy money or whatſoeuer elſe, I wil as is ſayd, that all entiere apperteine vnto the heyre, that is to Houſe of the Profeſſed Fathers in <hi>Rome:</hi> and I appoint and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the ſame for heyre in all &amp; euery of theſe thinges.</p>
                     <p>For the help of my Soule, I
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19250:62"/> leaue or preſcribe nothing, becauſe very<note place="margin">For the benefit of his ſoule.</note> little wil come vnto my Heyre, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſeing I neuer took care to heap vp money or to gather wealth: as alſo for that I truſt, or rather know, the piou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> charity of my Mother, to wit the Society of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> will not be wanting to help me, as it is neuer wanting to other of her Children, and as my ſelfe haue neuer beene wanting all my life tyme, to offer Sacrifices and prayers for ſuch as were departed of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>I nominate, for honours ſake my moſt Illuſtrious and Reuerend Lord, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall<note place="margin">The Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutour of his will, and what he left him.</note> 
                        <hi>Aldobrandino,</hi> for the Executour of this my will. I hope there will need no labour in the execution thereof: and I leaue vnto the ſame moſt Illuſtrious Lord (then which I haue nothing more deare) a vvoodden Croſſe filled vvith moſt pretious reliques, the names of which he ſhall find in a little deske, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with red ſilke.</p>
                     <p>This Will and Teſtament I will haue to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in force, the former two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing annulled, which in all thinges, and for all, I reuoke, make voide, and annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, notvvithſtanding that this Will
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19250:62"/> hath not perhaps been made with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſolemnityes (as the Law requireth) for the Bull of Clement the 8. in which leaue is giuen me to make my will, doth expreſly graunt me this liberty, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make it by ſimple letter, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writing ſubſcribed with mine own hand.</p>
                     <p>I <hi>Robert Bellarmyne</hi> doe diſpoſe, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, bequeath, and appoint by Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament as aboue, not only in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, but in any other better forme what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. The 23. day of Ianuary 1611.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="lat">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:63"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:63"/>
                  <p>IN FVNERE ROBERTI CARD. BELLARMINI ORATIO <hi>TARQVINII GALLVTII SABINI è Societate Ieſu.</hi> Habita Romae, in Templo Domus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſae eiuſdem Societatis, Idib. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctob. Anno. M. DC. XXI. <hi>Illustriſsimo Principi ODOARDO CARD. FARNESIO, Angliae Protectori &amp;c. dica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of the English College at Saint-Omer, featuring the seal of the Jesuites or Society of Jesus, a sunburst containing a cross over the letters IHS over three nails</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Iuxta Exemplar impreſſum <hi>Romae,</hi> apud Alexandrum Zannettum, 1621.</p>
                  <p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                        <body>
                           <p>SVPERIORVM PERMISSV.</p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:64"/>
                  <p>Imprimatur, ſi videbitur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendiſſ. P. Mag. Sacr. Palat. Apoſt.</signed>
                     <signed>P. Epiſcopus de Curte Viceſg.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>F. Greg. Donatus Magiſt. &amp; Soc. Reu. P. Fr. Hyacinthi Petronij Magiſt. Sacr. Palat. Apoſt. Ord. Praedic.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:64"/>
                  <head>ILL<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. PRINCIPI, ODOARDO FARNESIO S. R. E. CARD. AMPLISS. Angliae Protectori &amp;c. <hi>Tarquinius Gallutius F.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>VAS in priuato Funere haud multis antè diebus ROBERTI BEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARMINI Cardinalis expoſui laudes, eas, Illustriſſime Princeps, in tuo ſplendore proponam, ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducam in publicum. Hanc opinor au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciae meae facilè veniam dabis: qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt coniecturis aſſequor, ipſe mihi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19250:65"/> beatorum domicilio tribuit <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus.</hi> Reſpuiſset ille quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viuens hoc laudum ſuarum acroama, quod alioqui mortalibus eſt ita iucundum: ſed nunc, cùm tam pium prohibere non potest officium, ſi conſuli poſſet mortuus, reſponderet haud dubiè, placere ſibi virtutum ſuarum orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tibi potiſſimùm offerri, ac de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicari; Cui praecipuum ipſe ſemper honorem habuit; Cui libellum de cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesti felicitate pulcherrimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit; Cui etiam paulo ante obitum ſe debere profeſſus eſt plurimùm. Hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerat hanc ille à maioribus ſuis hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditariam obſeruantiam erga No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men iſtud, Domumue Farneſiam, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiorum altricem hominum, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bonorum apertam ſemper, &amp;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19250:65"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſpitalem ex ea quippe cum alijs longè plurimis, qui vel ſacram Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atus augustiſſimi Purpuram, vel ſummum Chriſtianae re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum adepti ſunt, ille quoque Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus olim prodijt, que <hi>Bellarminus</hi> &amp; auunculum habuit à genere, &amp; virtutum ſuarum idoneum, quod i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitaretur, Exemplar eſt nactus. Hunc, inquam, aduerſus Farneſiam gentem acceperat à ſuis quaſi tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latitium amorem, ac reuerentiam: ſed nominatim erga promeritum, ac virtutem tuam ſic erat effectus, vt qui faceret omnia temperatè, in te vno diligendo, obſeruandoue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum habere non videretur. Et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit quidem à te parem beneuolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſignificatiouem, ac gratiam; cùm
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19250:66"/> Tu praeter ceteros inſignem hominis doctrinam, &amp; ſanctimoniam admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus, non modo verbis ampliſſimis eum ſemper ornaueris, ſed eiuſdem quoque in actu vitae poſtremo res ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas ſingulas, ac pronunciata deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, notarique ſcripto volueris, quae tibi proponeres ad imitandum. Quin id quoque merito gloriaris, quòd tu, ſupremo loco ab eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſecratus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus, eorum clauſeris agmen &amp; numerum, qui tantam in eo genere ſunt adepti felicitatem. Eſt enim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo periucundum, à ſanctiſſimis, ac celebratiſsimis viris eiuſmodi mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus accipere, quod ſacrum nihilomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſſet ac ſanctum, quamqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nohis à gregarijs, &amp; communi ſanctitudine praeditis hominibus impartiretur.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19250:66"/> Vtinam pateretur iuſtae modus or ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, hic à me percenſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> omnia, quae de <hi>Bellarmini</hi> ſanctitate ſpectabili cupis agnſocere ſimul enim obſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer animo tuo, ſimul ſatisfacerem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis orbis terrarum, qui praeclarum hoc virtutum omnium ſpeculum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementer expoſcit. Sed explebunt hoc manus alij, qui vitam bominis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucleatè perſcrutabuntur omnem, quaeque ſapienter ab eo, acrectè facta ſunt opera, diligenter, accurateue perſequentur. Interim, Illuſtriſsime Princeps, haec pauca deliba, &amp; à me, atque à tota Sodalitate nostra, quam impendiò foues, vale plurimum, ac ſalue: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Chriſtianae Reipublicae or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to &amp; commodo diuturuum at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> incolumem praeſta.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:19250:67"/>
                  <head>ORATIO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AGNVM è Collegio Purpura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ſuperioribus hiſce die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extulimus hominem: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum ſanè parentem, ac pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronum amiſimus: magnum ipſa Religio Cuſtodem luget, ac Defenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem: magnum, vt ſemel dicam, mihi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo propoſitum argumentum, ROBER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVM BELLARMINVM Cardinalem, Tutorem, Praeſidem, Conſiliarium, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorem Chriſtianae Republicae magnum. Mentiuntur haud dubiè, ac ſaepe mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus imponunt Mathematici quidam dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Chaldaeorum inſtituti diſciplina, qui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinare ſe putant, ac futura praedicere: nec quiſquam paulò ſapientior eſt, qui genus hoc hominum, vt dixit ille, conſulenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus infidum, ſperantibus fallax, qui ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litioſam hanc artem commentis, &amp; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacijs illaqueantem plurimos, vetari legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſemper, ſemperue retineri non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queratur, Mirantur tamen aliqui, cur ex fallaci doctrina, reſponſa quaedam fortuita ſanè, atque inconſtantia, ſed euentum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum habentia, vulgoue probata pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiſcantur; tum praeſertim, cùm totius an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19250:67"/> futuras belli, paciſue viciſſitudines, aêris ſalubritatem aut luem, annonae pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, pecudum vale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udinem aut mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos, hominum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eritus &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unera, ex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroium notatione generatim, vniuerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſignificant. Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am profectò non nullis admirationem in hunc Bellarmini deceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum curioſiùs, quam par eſſet, intuentibus, mouit nuper luſtorum aliquis, qui p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciare non dubitauerat, hoc anno ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente magnum é viuis eſſe demigraturum Antiſtitem. Excita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at adeo plurimorum expectationem illa praedictio, perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentium, Ecquis ea Magni nominis appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione deſignaretur ad obitum? Sed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtim ambigua ſuſpicione liberauit eorum animos exemptus è mortalium numero Bellarminus: cuius tanta magnitudo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eſt, vt hunc demum eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e putauerint, cuius exitus è vita fortuitò fuiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et, &amp; caſu denuncia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us. Mihi quidem neque praedict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum harioli, neque vulgi ſimplex iſta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur, &amp; credula natio: ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umtamen ex illa interpretatione prorſus, id omnes exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimaſſe, idue me poſſe, probantibus vniuerſis, ac iure contendere, Magni co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnomentum multò ſane magis in purpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum hunc Antiſtitem cadere debere,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19250:68"/> quàm in eos, qui olim à magnitudine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum geſtarum illum ſibi titulum inuene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Eum enim verè magnum dici poſſe, atque hoc nomen in eo tantum modo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni debere crediderim, in quo virtus illa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendatur, quae quoniam humano fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigio ſuperior eſſe videtur, ac maior; ab officiorum praeceptoribus appellatur He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roica. haec autem non vna eſt militaris illa fortitudo, quam poëtae immanibus etiam, &amp; truculentis hominibus interdum attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buunt; ſed ipſius quoque temperantiae, manſuetudinis, ac modeſtiae, ſingularum denique virtutum apex, &amp; extremitas vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima praeclaro illo nomine cohoneſtatur. Nullis adeo virtutis Heroicae legibus inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemur, quó minùs hunc ſacri Senatus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratiſſimum, ac modeſtiſſimum Patrem dicere Magnum excellenti nomine debea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; cùm ipſis quoque lenioribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruere virtutibus Nomen illud Heroicum poſſit, ſi eum gradum eminentem, ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamue determinationem attingant, quae non tam in homines conuenire vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur, quàm in aliquos omni humano cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, atque ingenio celſiores. Quamquam ne illius quidem fortitudinis, cui ſolùm Heroicum nomen imperitia poëtarum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partit,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19250:68"/> ſi minùs expreſſam vim, certe ſimilitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aliquam in hoc homine prorſus, omninoue conſiderabimus, ſi eius intueri ſcripta illa volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imus, quorum impreſſione bellum Chriſtianae Reipublicae perduellibus acerrimum fecit, faciet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue quoad litterae loquentur, &amp; monumenta ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, quoad erit humanum genus, quoad ipſa rerum vniuerſitas communi populorum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um rogo, ac tumulo conflagrabit. Statuarum ſe poëta Pindarus eſſe gloriatur, &amp; dicit artificem: non tamen ea ſigna caelare, ac facere, quae vel tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, hominúmue iniuriae ſint obnoxia, vel motu careant, ac vita, vel ſua ſemper in baſi, &amp; loculamento conſiſtant; ſed carmina condere ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis meliora, quae terras, ac maria peruage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, quae victoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coronas toto terrarum orbe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferant, quae nullis ſint, aut belloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut alia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum calamitatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> procellis, ac te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtatibus oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lorietur hic etiam noſter, ea ſe compoſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe, ac reliquiſſe poſteritati armamenta doctrinae, quorum beneficio, ac vi, non in vna, vel altera terrarum ora, non vno, vel altero tempore, ſed vbique ac continenter implacabile bellum cum deſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ortibus olim geſſerit, geret<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſemper in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterum, vita quidem functus, ac ſpiritu caſſus, at in monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis illis aeternùm ſpirans, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ob rem pro Chriſtiana Religione feliciſſimè geſtam, ipſa nominis immortalitate ſuperſtes. Sed vt plani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19250:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:19250:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19250:70"/> explicatiuſue propoſitum attingam, ac ea, quae de doctrina dicenda eſſe arbitror, in loco di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, ac ſeparatim, ita ſtatuo: in Bellarmino, quem iure Magnum appellari debere contendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Antiſtitem, magnam oppidò fuiſſe ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, magnam religionem, ac pietatem, magnam rerum humanarum contemptionem, temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, manſuetudinem, modeſtiam, ac modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, ceteras denique virtutes huiuſmodi faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liores etiam magnas; hoc eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as, quae communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus egreſſae finibus, humanum viciſſe modum, menſuramue mortalitatis omnem ſuperaſſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deantur. Et quoniam doctrinae ſplendor eximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in hoc primo veſtibulo confeſtim occurrit, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ego ductum aduerſitoris vltrò, ac libentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè ſequar, qui &amp; clariſſimam praeferet ceteris vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus in itinere facem, &amp; Heroicam in hoc ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine laudem eſſe multo facillimè demonſtrabit.</p>
                  <p>Ex honeſtis, boniſue Maioribus in vrbe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiana, quod norunt vniuerſi, Bellarminus eſt natus; quibus vt ipſe continuò moribus ac pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate reſpondere ſtuduerit ſingulis, multò ſe tamen ſimiliorem exhibuit auunculo ſuo Marcello Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino Pontifici Maximo, religioſiſſimo, doctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, ac prudentiſſimo Viro, quem Chriſtianus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis tamquam è coelo per machinam in hoc Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum extemplo demiſſum effuſe gratulatus eſt, ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odem repente ſubductum vehementer indoluit.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19250:70"/> Anno aetatis 16. nondum exacto, humanaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pertaeſus, atque affectus faſtidio rerum, Sodalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem hanc noſtram infantem adhuc, &amp; prope creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem in cunis precibus expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ijt infimis: ſed cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à patre ad explorandam animi conſtantiam in quodam vico Ceruinorum attineretur, praeterqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod, operi futuro praeludens, ad paganos de Deo, deque Chriſtiani hominis officio conciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur aſſiduè, in conſanguineorum etiam aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Academia, vbi aliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alij ſcriptorem explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, orationem ipſe pro Milone Ciceronis egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam, atque vt antiquorum aliqui loquuntur, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationum Reginam auſus eſt illa aetate puer inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretari. quo tempore, vt eius quoque facultatis, in qua mirabili modo iuuentutis prodere ſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let ingenium, &amp; amoenitas animi, ſpecimen ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod daret, carmen fundere coepit, &amp; bonum, &amp; multiplex. nam cùm alia multa latina, popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue lingua poëmata fecit, tum vnum, quod pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum fuit, de virginitate praeclarum, &amp; eclogam, elegiamue de Rober<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i Nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij Cardinalis obitu longè pulcherrimas; quae in hominum honeſta corona pronunciatae, non modò cum acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſunt exceptae, verum etiam auditae cum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimis. Cum hac indole poſt aliquod tempus hanc Sodalitatem ingreſſus, illico coepit inter excellentia ingeniorum lumina, quibus etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tum effloreſcebat hic coetus, ita praefulgere, vt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicis
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19250:71"/> tantùm imbutus artibus, necdum ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cris initiatus, ſimul ad domeſticos de virtutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu ſtatis ex more diebus verba faceret, ſimul hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniores in Gymnaſio doceret litteras, ſimul ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cras explicaret in templo, tanta cum approbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quantam ne ipſi quidem veterani promere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur. In quo munere cum Monti-Regali Ciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padanorum Vrbi praeclaram initio nauaſſet ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae deinde, ac Patauij, tum denique Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neijs, in Vrbe Domina, prima noſtrorum hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iam inde ab initio Societatis altrice ſumma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutus eſt laudem: vbi eum nobiliſſimi, diſertiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miue Senatores, quorum illa Reſpublica floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima, &amp; ſingulari ſapientia regitur, &amp; abundat numero, non cum admiratione ſolùm audiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt è loco ſuperiore dicentem, verùm etiam ad extremum opera perfunctum ſua, &amp; diſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem exoſculari cum pietate voluerunt. Pauciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi quidem fuere, tamen fuerunt aliqui ad milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſtudia ſic facti, vt exercitus antè duxerint, &amp; copias, quàm aut in tirocinio fuerint, aut inter gregarios ſtipendia fecerint: id quod nominatim contigiſſe Lucullo ferunt; qui propter incredibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ingenij magnitudinem ſubito ingreſſus eſt imperator in Aſiam, cum fuiſſet rei bellicae rudis ex Vrbe profectus. Sed quod in re militari tam rarum exemplum eſt, id ego video in omni do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae laudae Bellarmino adoleſcenti ſingulariter
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19250:71"/> eſſe conceſſum. vt enim Auguſtinus omnium illa genera rerum, obſcuriſſimo ab Ariſtotele ſtylo deſcripta, nullo magiſtro praeeunte percepit; ſic ipſe difficillimas quaſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, grauiſſimaſue docere aggreſſus artes, optimus repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te magiſter apparuit earum rerum, quarum aut nunquam, aut certè vix fuiſſet ante diſcipulus. Miſſus in Belgium eſt nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Theologiae cognitione penitus inſtitutus in ſchola, nec vllis inſtructus Ordinibus ex ijs, qui Sacerdotio praeparant viam; ita prorſus, vt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe habuerit Leodij minores omnes, &amp; è maiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ac ſacris vnum accipere, reliquis autem Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daui à Cornelio illo Ianſenio, cuius in Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio laus, &amp; perfecta lucubratio eſt, aliquando fuerit inſignitus. Et tamen illa aetate iuuenis, ac ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſacrarum interea monumenta literarum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina concione Louanij ſic interpretabatur in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis, in exedra Theologiam, excellentem illam, diuina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue ſcientiam ita docebat, vt clamoribus vndique factis, ad eum audiendum vtriuſque re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cauſa ab innumerabili multitudine cum pugilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, &amp; palimpſeſtis ex tota prouincia concurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur. Hic videlicet, vbi nouitius praeceptor inter imperatoria munera tam egregia rudimenta po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebat, meditari coepit bellum, quod poſtea, &amp; indixit animoſe, &amp; ſuſcepit ardenter, &amp; promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit conſtanter, &amp; bona demum ex parte profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gauit aduerſus Eccleſiae transfugas, quibus in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19250:72"/> terrarum orbe vix habet alios hoſtes Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na religio capitaliores. Vagabantur multis ſanè locis, &amp; Chriſti fundum, regnumue vaſtabant haec monſtra, ferocitate formidoloſa, veneno peſtifera, numero infinita. Repebant humi quaedam, mordebantue praetereuntes, quaſi dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cones, &amp; colubri per inſidias: alia voluntabantur in coeno, nec extra popinas, &amp; ganeas egredie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur: alia velut Harpyiae quaedam Angelorum illum panem, &amp; Regum delicias conabantur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere: alia tamquam tauri cornibus, pedibuſue aras, ac Caelitum imagines euertebant: alia Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus, ac Dynaſtis infenſa ſanguine reſperge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant vrbes, templa, fora, loca omnia vulneribus, ac caede cruentabant. Singula denique ſeparatim ipſa per ſe monſtra erant immania, communiter, &amp; coniunctim Hydram componere videantur, cuius vulnera periculoſiora eſſent, &amp; foecundio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, quàm ſanitas. Non tamen eſt tanto labore, periculoue deterritus hic Imperator: ſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parata ſibi diſciplinarum, litterarum, linguaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que omnium copia tanta<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quantam ne multi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſimul homines aſſequi poſſent, claſſicum cecinit illud, quo tamquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eonis rugitu perter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refactae minores belluae, ad meditandum effugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um intra latibula ſe condiderunt. Bezae quippe co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yphaei, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> anteſignani repentino veluti ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine percuſſi è Geneuae gurguſtio demum audita
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19250:72"/> vox eſt, vi quadam diuina, &amp; quaſi machina veritatis extorta; cùm primò illo controuerſiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſpecto volumine, vbi de Pontificis auctoritate diſſeritur, exclamare coactus eſt, Hic liber enim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerò nos perdidit. Eoſdem alij quoque clamores emiſerunt, ac lacrymas, impe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dioque cogitare coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perunt, qua ratione ruinae poſſent occurrere, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis imminere ceruicibus intuebantur. Confeſtim in Brita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nia certu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excitauere ſuggeſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſedemue conſtituerunt à ceteris ſeiunctam, &amp; propria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex qua refelleretur accuratè, ac ſedulò Bellarminus. hoc enim confutato, putabant arce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnem Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae religionis amoliri ſe poſſe; quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eorum vnus ſcriptis ad Virum primarium hiſce litteris haud dubie ſignificauit: <q rend="inline">Gaudere ſe, quòd Bellarmini vulgata eſſent opera, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lectione planiſſimè demu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, certiſſimèque poſſet intelligi, quid in vnaquaque de religione contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſia Romanae vindices Eccleſiae cenſerent, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue medulla eſſet Pontificij dogmatis intima, quae non magis in ipſo Pontifice, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ieſuitis (ſic enim ipſe loquitur) eſſe crederetur.</q> Infelicem, &amp; eum, quem omnino merebatur exitum nacta eſt tam inſolens, ac putida diligentia: cum ex ea ſchola permulti de ſuo iam dubitantes errore, plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi quoque mutato planè conſilio, atque ad ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem conuerſi quotidie digrederentur. Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerunt adeo, fruſtra ſe demum conari clauam
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19250:73"/> illam infringere, quam Hercules haberet in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu: &amp; iam tota Britannia in eos, qui curiosè ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruateue meditabundi cernuntur in via, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune quaſi prouerbium dicitur, De Bellarmino refellendo, tamquam de Althantico mari per ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tylani exorbendo cogitare. Quin ita ſibi perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerant omnes; Bellarminum ſtatura procera, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue ſupra modum eminenti praeditum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe natura; nec ijs habebant fidem, qui teſtaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hominem ſe Romae, alibiue vidiſſe non ita magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac paruo potius inſtructum corporis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu, quàm excelſo. Neque enim fieri poſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabant, vt praegrandi quoque ſtatura, &amp; corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non eſſet ille, qui animo, ac doctrina fuiſſet contra Gigantes iſtos, Titanaſue Centimanus. In ſumma, veritatis ineluctabilis eſt vis, fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue teſtes adornantur aduerſus conſcientiae iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, quod corrumpi, deprauariue non poteſt. Nam cùm omni lapide commoto, efficere ſe non poſſe cernerent, vt vel captionibus, ac praeſtigijs, vel fictis etiam fabulis huius hominis eleuarent exiſtimationem, imminuerent fama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; coeperunt eunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſi quoque mirificè praedicare, verbiſue ac re illum plurimi pendere, quem aſpernari ſine ſua vituperatione non poſſent. Bataui quippe, ſicuti nuper accepimus, in ſua ipſorum publica bibliotheca Bellarminum vel primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe volunt, vel collocant inter primos: &amp; alij, qui aduerſus
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19250:73"/> eum ſcribere tamen aliquid audent, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munem reueriti populorum opinionem, eumdem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, vt nos ad hominem exornandum Oratores haud alios, quàm vituperatores iſtos quaerere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamus. Placet iſtorum verba, quoniam hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtimonia ſunt, de ſcripto pene, ac volumine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Magnum,</hi> inquit eorum aliquis (Caecilium illum alloquens Angliae Quaeſtorem) <hi>magnum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Bellarminus: de quo homine cùm meam opinionem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reres, reſpondi vt ſenſi, me illum iudicare virum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè doctum, ingenio felici, iudicio ſubtili, lectione multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici praeditum; qui ſoleret etiam apertius, ac ſimplicius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, quàm ceteri, argumentum preſsius vrgere, atque ad cauſam arctius adhaereſcere: cumue legiſset omnes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentationes, reſponſio neſue, ſelegit quas iudicaret eſse neruoſiore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Arduum ſane opus,</hi> exclamat alius, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmini quaeſtiones illas infinitas in certa volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na relatas, admirans, <hi>arduum opus, quod exigit ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam prope infinitam, non modo variarum diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, &amp; linguarum, ſed etiam totius antiquitatis, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium hiſtoriarum, ac temporum. multa iſto in opere, atque inſtituto peluti pila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as actes agmine facto oportet homini <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe, cùm in tantis rebus, argumentiſue ſcientiam adeo multiplicem deſiderari putauerit, vt haereticos non v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s generis, ſed varia variorum examina vna acie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterneret.</hi> Auditis elogiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inimico profectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex ore, ac veritatem apertiſſima confeſſione de mendacio triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phantem? euerſos ſe, proſtratoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> profitentur.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19250:74"/> ſed ne ſolidum victori concedere gaudium vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, &amp; ſe pythones iſti, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minuto iam capite, cauda tamen, ac reliquo corpore commoueant, in huius partem laudis, ac gloriae collegas etiam vocant, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auxilio Bellarminus illa tam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua monumenta perfecerit. non enim inducere poſſunt animum, opus ita ſpiſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tantiſue diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatibus impeditum vnius labore hominis, ac ſtudio confici, expediriue potuiſſe. Scio equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem hoc co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentum iugulatum eſſe nuperrimè, viri doctiſſimi oratione, ac ſtylo, qui &amp; codices ex Romani Collegij bibliotheca produxit auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphos Bellarmini manu perſcriptos, &amp; verè, ſanctèque teſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt, hominem ſe vidiſſe cùm quaeſtiones illas exararet, non modo nullis adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis eius laboris, operaeue conſortibus, ſed ne amanuenſibus quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut exceptoribus accerſitis, addam tamen etiam ego ſymbolam meam, &amp; i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos, qui ſuo iudicio errare, ac decipi volunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitos ſanè, repugnanteſue omni prorſus errore liberabo.</p>
                  <p>Eſt his, qui Bellarmini laborem, &amp; gloriam cum alijs communicatam volunt, ingenium, vt credo, mediocre, memoria fortaſſe non mala, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina, quae ſupra litteraturam non attollatur, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium haud multum, comeſſationes, compota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneſue creberrimae, impietas in Caelites, in homines arrogantia non ferenda: quibus cum
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19250:74"/> moribus diuina ſe conciliare ſapientia non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, quae modeſtis, ac bonis viris gratiam dare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uperbis elatiſue ſe reſiſtere profitetur. Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no fuit ingeniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſingulare, ordine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucido perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax, verſatile, factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad omnia; memoria, vt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel dica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pene diuina, quae quicquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egeret, ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beretue ſtatim, ac ſubitò reciperet, quicquid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepiſſet, fideliſſimè, conſtantiſſimeque retineret. Fuit ſtudium ita pertinax, &amp; tam inſatiabile, vt, non dico diem ſine linea, ſed ne momentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poris elabiſine operae pretio pateretur; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perantia verò incredibilis, vigiliae plurimae, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, animiue demiſſio diſciplinarum ſtudio ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior. Vultis igitur acutiſſimi Silones ex me diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quid cauſae ſit, cur ille aduerſum vos, hoc eſt aduerſus impietatem, ſine ſocijs, auxilijſue ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere potuerit opus, quod tam multa librarijs aëra meretur, quod in ſola Germania vigeſima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet editionem, quod immortalitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi iure pollice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod cùm fieret, multorum, vt dicitis, &amp; creditis ipſi, defatigauit ingeniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; vos autem col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato ſtudio, longo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poſt tempore librum profera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel non magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel quatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, certe non bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; qui vix natus exareſcat, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum edicto proſcriptus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> obliteratus incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio? vultis inquam id ex me noſſe? poſſum enim hoc vobis oraculum facilè reddere, totumue Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byllae folium vno verbo recitare. Cúm vos in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19250:75"/> viola decumbebatis, &amp; pluma, ille vigilans, ac pro religione velut excubias agens, in rerum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinarum, humanarumue contemplatione ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabatur. Cùm vos in voluptatibus eratis, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatione corporis, ille temperantia, ieiunioue oblectans animum, vel in Patrum ſanctiſſimoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> legendis, euoluendiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> monumentis erat totus, vel feriatus à ſtudio cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperis colloquebatur &amp; Deo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cùm veſtris vos innixi viribus &amp; ingenio, ſtylum in Eccleſiam, hoc eſt, in Chriſti corpus armaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; ille ſibi diffiſus, ac doctrinae ſuae, tela prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat quae regereret in aduerſarios, pia plus preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, quàm lucubrationibus &amp; vigilijs, plus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtia, quàm minis, plus commodorum omnium deſpicientia, quàm rerum copia communitus.</p>
                  <p>Sed hae nimirum illae virtutes ſunt, quas in Bellarmino fuiſſe ſummas huius orationis initio dixi. pergam igitur, atque à doctrina gradum faciam ad ea, quae cum illa ſingulari ſcientia vinculo prorſus admirabili, ac perdifficili copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione coniunxit. Quàm enim arduum ſit, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niores quaſdam, manſuetioreſue virtutes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae praeſtabili, &amp; rerum omnium cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſubnectere, ſcimus omnes, qui literarum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquo colore leuiter aſperſi, neceſſe habemus aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duè ſpiritus, atque animos premere, hoc eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere, ne nobis ipſis ſapientes nos eſſe videamur ideo, quòd ſupra vulgares, atque imperitos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19250:75"/> plus aliquid intelligamus. Neque verò il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam hic ego vitae partem attingendam puto, quae nondum iniecta purpura, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uce tantummodo lucebat ſua: cùm ſit eius conditionis ita propria moderatio, &amp; rerum humanarum contemptio, vt quamquam dicere ſingularia poſſum, nihil ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praeter modum adimrabile me dicturum eſſe confidam. Sin antem ex acceſſione purpurae. non modò nihil eum de modeſtia, deue animi demiſſione, nihil de felicitatis, ac rerum omnium deſpicientia remiſiſſe, verum etiam eas virtutes auctiores longè feciſſe, ac meliores oſtendero, aliquid ſine dubio proferam in medium ab ea vitae, fortunaeue mutatione vehementer abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens. Vt enim hic ordo Purpuratorum illuſtriſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus omnis planè moderationis, omniumue virtutum ſua ſanctitate ſit cuſtos; ſplendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem tamen haberet eiuſmodi, qui perſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat interdum virorum quoque bonorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem, habet tantam ſupremo cum honore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitatem, vt animum alioqui firmum, ac ſtabilem poſſit aliquantulum eius cupiditate la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>befactare. Sed non labefactauit animum eius, qui purpuram illam, hoc eſt, honorem primo proximum tam ingratis accepit, quàm alij ſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter expectant, qui tacitum, &amp; quietum plus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maret o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium, quàm alij turbidam, inquietam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue felicitatem, qui faſtigium omne dignitatis,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19250:76"/> &amp; culmen finitimum putaret eſſe ruinae locum. Erat iam Bellarminus, quamquam ipſe frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam fugeret, hominumue notitiae ſubduceret ſe, nomine celebratiſſimus, &amp; fama<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fuerat iam olim à Cardinale Borromaeo Sanctiſſimo, quem nunc aris colimus, &amp; ſacris, expetitus ardenter, fruſtraue Mediolanum é Belgio, Prouincialibus enixè repugnantibus, accerſitus. fuerat à Sixto V. Pont. Max. cum Henrico Cardinale Caieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Legato difficili ſane tempore miſſus in Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. fuerat ab alijs deinceps in dubijs de religione quaeſtio nibus ſaepe conſultus. à Clemente Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo diligi, honorari<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praeter ceteros, ac multo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime videbatur. Animaduertebat ipſemet eius in ſe Pontificis illuſtria quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; peculiaria beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiae ſigna: ſed vir antiqui moris, ac probitatis ſuſpicari ſerò coepit, ad Purpuratoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſimum ſe deſtinari. Peſtem adeo ſibi ratus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minere, admonet de ſuſpicione ſua communem familiae noſtrae Praeſidem, ac Rectorem in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, oratue vt tantum periculum à ſe, ac prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exemplu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à tota quoque Sodalitate defendat. Dum ſibi, dum publicae rei tanto cum ſtudio, ac ſollicitudine cauet, ecce tibi qui eum nunciarent Cardinalem eſſe iam factum, vetarentue domo pedem efferre, niſi ab eius voluntate diſcedere vellet, cuius imperio traheretur ad purpuram. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres afflatum ſidere peſtilenti, non ingrato nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19250:76"/> verberatum. latebras meditabatur, &amp; ſugam, antiqua proculdubio renouaturus exempla, niſi fuiſſet aliorum iudicio, atque auctoritate prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus. Quippe animi dubius, inopſue conſilij, ſapientiores Patres, &amp; doctiores, quorum ipſe in Poenitentiario Diui Petri Collegio Praefectus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, ac Moderator, in conſultationem accitos an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiè percontatur, Ecquid ſibi faciendum in illo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, ac rerum articulo cenſeant; remanſionem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſuadeant, an tacitam ad Pontificem abitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt de ſuo eum dolore, deue Sacramento, quo eiuſmodi vetabatur honorem capeſſere, faceret in priuato colloquio certiorem. Reſpondent ad vnum omnes, id integrum non videri, nec eſſe deliberationi locum, vbi praecepto tam amplo ad reſiſtendum domi cogeretur. Abit è concilio tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis: &amp; quoniam clauſa videbat effugia, quaerere molimina coepit, certo ad Aldobrandinum Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalem homine dimiſſo, qui aditum ad Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficem ſuo nomine poſtularet. Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne iacta quidem hac ancora ſolùm co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenderetur, eundum fuit in coetum, vbi ceteri Collegae hominem operie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur. Antequam de more tonderetur, antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noui ordinis indueretur veſtibus, diù, multumue laboratum eſt. Itum perfectis omnibus in coena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ex more, vbi gratulationes erant, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut in natalitijs epulis, &amp; laeta colloquia. ſolus ipſe interea lugere, ac lacryman, ſolus angi, &amp;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19250:77"/> fortunam complorare ſuam, tamquam in ſilicer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio funeſtorum eſſet, non in conuiuio Purpura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum. Ductus denique cum reliquis ad Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, cum ſui conſilij rationem atque impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, quo ab honore delato prohiberetur ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus eſſet exponere, indicta contumaciae poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, niſi deſiſteret, ac ſilere continuò iuſſus, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicem aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſuppoſuit iugo, quod citra lethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feri peccati culpam detrectare non poterat. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benter haererem hoc loco, vbi magnanimae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptionis offendimus exemplum ita rarum, vt gloriari pene poſſimus, hoc noſtro ſaeculo natum eſſe. libenter, inquam, hic immorarer, niſi virtutes hominis antiquas in hoc honoris gradu retentas, amplificataſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, niſi nouas etiam expoſiturus eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quas in idonea propoſuit ſcena, ſuo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> velut in lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine collocauit.</p>
                  <p>Principiò, quemadmodum in commentario legi, quem ſuo ipſe chirographo conſignatum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquit, id apud ſe certiſſimo decreto ſancitum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit, vt priſtini parſimoniam victus, piaeue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem precationis, ac ceteram viuendi ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem antiquam perpetuò retineret: deinde, vt nullos à Pontifice redditus, prouentúſue peteret annuos, nulla prorſus à Principibus acciperet munera, quibus occaecantur etiam lyncei: tum, vt nullas ſibi pararet opes, quibus affines, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinei redderentur opulentiones. Quae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19250:77"/> quàm exaggeratè, cumulatè que praeſtiterit omnia, duorum &amp; viginti decurſus annorum, ſemper aequabilis, ac ſimilis ſui, ſanctiſſima de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum innocentis vitae concluſio declarauit. Quod enim attinet ad diuinarum commentationem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ac pias preces, numquam commiſit, quin eius ſtudij cauſa de nocte conſurgeret, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecit ſemper, vt ad veterem vſum aliquid plus tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; vacationis accederet: quod ad cibi, vitae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que degendae modum; &amp; cum priori temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ieiunia ſingulis hebdomadis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erna coniunxit, &amp; à generali Societatis noſtrae Moderatore legem efflagitauit, qua ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pellectilem, familiam, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum omne domeſticum veluti certiſſima re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula metire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur. De prouentibus autem quàm ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil omnino laboraret, aliàs quidem ſemper, ſed tunc maxime demonſtrauit, cùm poſt accepti ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris initia, nullis ipſe copijs inſtructus, deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti penſionem Epiſcopo non copioſo remiſit tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, condonauitue minimè rogatus in perpetuum, &amp; Clementi Pontifici opulentum ei, quod primo quoque tempore ſuppeteret ſacerdotium polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi conſtanter affirmatèque reſpondit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid hoc eſſet diuitiarum, &amp; opulentiae alijs ſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benter, vltròque concedere, ſibi ſportulam, &amp; cubiculum in ea Societate, cuius etiam tum pars eſſet aliqua, deeſſe non poſſe. Suſcepit ille qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem aliquando Capuae Sacerdotium, &amp; quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19250:78"/> ita iubebatur, eius ciuitatis Antiſtitem ſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt fieri: ſed vtrum in eo quaeſtum pecuniae, an animarum facere compendium vellet, ab ijs intelligite, qui totam eius muneris ineundi, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curandiue rationem in hunc modum expoſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Principem Vrbis aedem, ipſamue domum Archiepiſcopi malè materiatas, &amp; ſqualore obſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas haud mediocri ſumptu primo loco refecit, nec feſtum vllum ire ſinebat diem, quo non ipſemet in templo concionem haberet. Deinde numero familiarum deſcripto, quarum vel anguſta res eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, vel grauis inopia, ſingulis menſibus certa pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniae ſumma ſubleuabat ſingulas: denique vt ne ijs quidem deeſſet, qui vicatim, oppidatimue ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem emendicant, iuſſit in ipſo domus atrio, veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulòque diribitores eſſe, qui petentibus aduenis quotidiè cibatum, ac nummos impertirentur. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hoc inſtitutum in obeunda quoque prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, &amp; ditione, quam ſingulis omnino luſtrabat annis, per pagos vbique concionabundus, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratè retinuit; neminem vmquam paſſus abire va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum ex ijs, quos aliqua premi rerum egeſtate cognouiſſet. In quo genere quoniam vnum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur eſſe, quod exponi ſolitariè velit, ac ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim enarrari, non committam, vt temerè cum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris inuoluatur.</p>
                  <p>Nihil in tota ſui muneris adminiſtratione prius habuit, aut antiquiùs, quàm vt corrigeret
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19250:78"/> populoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> capita ſacerdotes: inter quos cum vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offendiſſet alea iam infamem, &amp; talo, nec vllis aut verbis aut minis reuocare poſſet ab angiportis in templum, rogauit hominem quid eſſet cauſae, cur tam impotenter ab aris, &amp; ſacrificio ad alue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um raperetur, ac pyrgum. Reſponder, rem ſibi domi curtam eſſe, nec facile, niſi per ludum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere poſſe rationibus ſuis. Extemplò (videre manſuetudinem ne dicam, an liberalitatem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtis?) extemplò numerata pecunia, omnem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li quaeſtum, ac lucrum aleae repraeſentauit, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauitue, vt quoties tantumdem, aut plus e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam argenti vellet, toties ad accipiendum ſine rubore, ac verecundia reuerteretur. Emendatus ille con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtim (quis autem ea charitate non emendare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?) emendatus inquam, &amp; redditus exaleatore ſacerdos, toti ciuitati miraculum fuit. Ne aliud quidem huic omni ex parte perſimile obtegi ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentio, aut negligenter, &amp; per incuriam praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poteſt exemplum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſt enim hoc etiam ſpectabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, non liberalitatis modò, ſed etiam charitatis, ac manſuetudinis argumentum. Externus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, profugus, ac vagus ementito cum habitu, impuraue ad latus adiuncta pellice ſacerdos, ſiue caſu, ſine conſilio delatus eſt Capuam. vbi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſus, &amp; patefactus, qui carceres, ac trire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes expectare meritò poterat, abſtractus à mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricula, poenitentia luſtratus, toga demu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indutus,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19250:79"/> ac pallio, reperit apud Bellarminum Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitem eam animi ſalutem, ac vitae, quam ei diuturna illa, &amp; erratica deſperatio denegabat. Accipite verò nune, non dicam probabilis aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiae, cuius ille vel vacuum nomen aduerſabatur, ſed piae cuiuſdam cupiditatis, &amp; parſimoniae ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Veniebat cum ceteris ſacerdotibus in odae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, canebatue quotidie, non ea tantùm gratia, vt alijs praeiret exemplo, verum etiam, vt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam Capuae Archiepiſcopus ex inſtituto veteri Canonicus item eſt, ſua ipſe quoq, diurna ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, quae pauperibus elargiretur, excerperet. haec enim quia priuato illo labore, tamue ſtudioſo parabat incommodo, dicebat verè, propriêque ſe dare deſuo, cetera, que capiebantur ex ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij fructibus, ex alieno ſe dare ſibi videbatur. Non poſſum omnia perſequi, nec vna tantùm oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne complecti, quae per hoc benignitatis, ac mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericoroiae ſtudium edidit opera commemoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, monumentiſue digniſſima ſempiternis. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratiam omnis pecunia, exhauſtus propè iam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ipſe liberalitatis ac beneficentiae fundus: non aerarium, quod ei nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vmquam fuerat, ſed hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, cellae, pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuaria vacua iam erant, &amp; inania<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neque enim ille cibaria, non veſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non culcitram, non pallia ſupereſſe domi patiebatur. Reclamare omnes oeconomi, &amp; rei familiaris adminiſtri mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ſerio, ne viatici quidem aliquid reliquum
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19250:79"/> eſſe ad habendum in Vrbem iter, cuius, extincto Clemente Pontifice, propter futura comitia ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitas impendebat: cum ille interea id ſolùm ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a monita reſpondere ſatis haberet, auerſari ſe ſuperuacaneam ſecuturae diei prouidentiam, nec ſibi quicquam odioſius eſſe, quàm quae veritatis oraculo damnaretur, de futuro, ac de craſtino co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitationem. Et quoniam hoc Chriſti Seruatoris effatum firmiſſime conſignauerat animo, eam perpetuô retinuit ad obitum vſque conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ac diſciplinam, vt Calendis Ianuarij, cùm accepti, datiue conſuluiſſet ephemeridas, eroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri continuò iuberet quicquid ex anno priori ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſſet. Neque enim eum annum auſpicari ſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè credebat, qui domum ſuam omni ſpoliatam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendi preſidio non inuenieret. Et dubitabimus, vtrum illud quoque promiſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exſoluerit, quod tertio loco tum fecit, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtatim inter Ampliſſimos Patres adlectus, ſecum ipſe, ac Deo teſte ſibi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuit, nullas ſe collecturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opes, quibus agnatos, ac poſteros opimaret? O Teſtamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illud tuum, Bellarmine, pulcherrimae teſtimonium tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae, ac paupertatis! Vultis hic ego reſignem tabulas, quas decimo circiter ab hinc anno con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecerat, &amp; ſupremam hominis innocentiſſimi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem, aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue pronunciem totum? <hi>Corpus meum,</hi> inquit, <hi>efferri iubeo ſine deſignatoribus, &amp; pompa; nec in edito lecto, ſed in humili, vulgariue feretro collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="134" facs="tcp:19250:80"/> volo, nullis ornatum inſignibus, aut flabellis.</hi> Non potuit huic obtemperari mandato, quia Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Maximo viſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſtaliter: ſed profectò quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum imperarat, faciendum neceſſario ſic fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet, niſi eius haeredes inopiae, qui domus huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce fuerunt Patres, tum ad alia multa, tum ad haec etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſta peragenda nonnihil ex corrogata ſtipe contuliſſent. <hi>Ad expiationem animae meae nullam ego deſigno, legoue pecuniam, cui cogendae, cumulandaeúe nullis vmquam temporibus operam dedi: ſed ſpero, ſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mihi non defuturam Parentem, Altricemue meam Sodali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atem illam, cuius ego defunctis ſocijs pro mea viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li parte non defui. Fratri meo,</hi> (erat enim tum ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes) huic aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fratri ſuo quid expectatis, aut opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namini relicturum eſſe? apud argentarios, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptores pecuniam? domi ſigna marmorea, vel auream veſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? foris oppida, vel latifu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dia? ò alieni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſima Bellarmini á co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cogitatione conſilia! <hi>Fratri meo reddi volo pictam in tabula Octaui Clement is effigiem.</hi> haec eſt tota legati ſumma, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fraternae monumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opulentiae, tam parui reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modati. <hi>Angelo nepoti meo</hi> (viuebat hic etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cùm teſtamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conderetur) <hi>dari iubeo pictas tabulas duas, alteram Roberti Cardinalis de Nobilibus, altera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Diui Caroli Borromaei, &amp; argenteam crucem Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam ornatam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> reliquijs, quam e collo penſilem gerere mihi mos est.</hi> Ne huic quidem, aut ceteris aliquid am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius teſtamento relinquit. Superſunt enim alij
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19250:80"/> ex paterno, maternoue genere probae indolis adoleſcentes, quos indonatos propter inopia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe permittit, nec aliqua parte huius, quae nulla pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pemodum eſt, haereditatis aſpergit. Sed ire ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite iuuenes optimi, quae fortunae rapit iniquitas, &amp; inconſtantia. magna vobis à patruo, auuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue veſtro traditur, &amp; legatur haereditas, qui tanta cum omnium in ſe beneuolentia vixit, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta cum gloria deceſſit è viuis. Vidiſtis qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſenſu diligeretur ab omnibus, quanta mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnium co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend atione celebraretur. vidiſtis in morbo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premo adeuntem ad illum ſingulari cum amoris ſignificatione Pontifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vidiſtis ad eius genua primarios accidentes viros, manu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exoſculantes, aliquid religionis cauſa depoſcentes ex ijs, quae ille vel vſu tractaret, vel gereret corpore. vidiſtis denique illo demortuo, totius in hoc templu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Romae concurſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vndamue populi, militum perrumpentis cuſtodiam, &amp; corpus, aut lectum manu contingere geſtientis. Huius vos amoris, &amp; gloriae ab eo, ſi neſcitis, abſque teſtamento, &amp; ſyngrapha ſcripti eſtis haeredes, in huius vos aſſis, &amp; patronij partem venitis; quam, ſi ſapitis, Attali conditionibus anteferre debetis. Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim improbi parentes nullam perniciem, peſtemue creant maiorem liberis ſuis, quàm cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> odium ſibi conflant, &amp; maleuolentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> popularem; ſic innocentes, &amp; boni maiores nullam tradunt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19250:81"/> poſteris opulentiorem haereditatem, quàm cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Principu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi demerentur amorem, &amp; beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam ciuium. Has videlicet opes ipſi vos ab il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la pauperate decerpetis: demonſtrabimini prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euntium digito: relegetur in ore veſtro Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalis optimi dignitas, &amp; maieſtas: diligetur in idole virtus, ac ſanctitas; ipſa demu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vos, niſi degeneres eſſe volueritis, honoratiſſimi patrui promerita redundabunt.</p>
                  <p>Ceterùm iniuria virtutum ſit, in eo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopere diuitiarum, opumue contemptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem admirari, quem excellentiora bona quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp; potiora, hoc eſt ſummum hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem in terris, ac vitam ipſam ſcimus incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili magnanimitate neglexiſſe. Dixi de hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris deſpicientia ſanè multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cùm demonſtraui, quanto cum ſenſu, ac dolore ſe paſſus eſt inter Purpuratos adſcribi; ſed dicenda ſunt ampliora. Neque enim ex eorum numero Bellarminus fuit, qui cùm honores ingratis acceperint, in acceptis deinde, quae humanae mentis eſt inconſtantia, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi placere paulatim incipiunt, &amp; maiores vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiùs expetere, quàm minores ante repudiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Non hanc ille moru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſimilitudinem, ac varietatem vmquam oſtendit: ſed eodem vultu ſemper honore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intuitus, quo eum olim repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter accepiſſet, auditus eſt aliquando cum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret, ſibi videri fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mas aſpicere ſuo corpori cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumfuſas,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19250:81"/> cùm ſe mitra indutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; purpura con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templaretur. Quin à probatiſſimis ego teſtibus accepi, atque abijs ipſis, quibus cum animi ſui conſilia communicauit, ſedulò de ſe abdicando, deponendaue purpura deliberaſle; nec ante de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiſſe, quam intelligeret, ſplendide ſane, atque ad aucupanda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctimoniae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amam appoſitè, ſed fruſtra, caſſoue conatu id ſe petiturum, quod ne Petro quidem Damiani prorſus, omnique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum fuiſſet ex parte. Tanta quippe dignitas, ac ſanctitas huius purpurae putatur eſſe, vt inter res illas euanidas, ac fluxas, quibus ad ſeuerioris vitae ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaerendam remitti nuncius à pijs, ac religioſis hominibus ſolet, numerari non poſſe videatur. Quae profectò cauſa Cardinales olim impulit, vt cum Ardicinus ſecundus à Porta, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine hoc ampliſſimo relicto, digreſſus eſſet ad Monachos, ab Innocentio Pont VIII. qui eam illi veniam inuitus dederat, vt reuocaretur in Collegium, quotidianis &amp; precibus, &amp; queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monijs efflagitarint.</p>
                  <p>Vnus tamen eſt in hoc honoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curriculo ſcopulus, quem pauciſſimi praeternauigant; vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illicium eſt, quo etiam callidi capiuntur, ac boni; vltimus ille mimiru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gradus, &amp; ſuprema poteſtas, qua partibus explentur omnibus ipſa vota morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. quippe animus etiam moderatus, ac tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perans cauſas ſibi videtur habere probabiles,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19250:82"/> cur apicern illum exoptet, in quo grauiſſimi Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, &amp; prima illa ſanctitatis antiquae lumina pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſionem, caſumue reformidarunt. Sed hic ſcopulus, &amp; breuia, hae tam artificioſae periculi latentis illecebrae illum fallere non potuerunt, qui &amp; curioſè diſcrimina perpenderet omnia, &amp; nihil in humanis, niſi quod eſt humile, tutum putaret, &amp; nominatim ab illo culmine ſibi time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam à ſaxo naufragijs opportuno. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciabat enim definiendo, idue crebris vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſermonibus ſolitus erat, Pontificiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> munus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem periculoſiſſimum, ac periculum laborio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe. Et quia circumſpecti, ac ſuſpicioſi gubernatoris eſt, etiam ea, quae non eueniunt, ſed tamen accidere poſſunt, animo ſecum ante peragere, dixit aliquando, gaudere ſe, quòd qui ad purpurae dignitatem ineuitabili praeceptione fuiſſet, ac neceſſitate compulſus, ad ſupremum Eccleſiae Sacerdotium adigi non poſſet imperio; cùm tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praecipendi ius in interregno quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum exiſtimabat ipſe, ſit nemini. Sic enim paratus erat ad id quoque muneris, honoriſue repudiandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt putaret, Cardinalium ſuffraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione omnium, ac volunate ſe cogi non poſſe; in ea tantum opinione decipi ſe paſſus, &amp; monito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, quem etiam audiuit, hoc vno loco requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, qui ſcriptis, ac doctrina totum terrarum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem inſtituiſſet. Cum hac ergo praeparatione,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19250:82"/> munimentoue Conclaue primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ingreſſus, cùm officij cauſa Patres Ampliſſimos, vt occaſio ſeſe dabat alloqueretur, &amp; ſalutaret aliquos, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebat, ne ſibi clauum Eccleſiae traderent, qui ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus duceret à maioribus aetate longaeuis, ac viua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſimis: periculum ſubeſſe, ne Pontificem vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nonagenarium. Altius haec in aliquorum pectus deſcendere poterant, quàm quae facetè di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, &amp; commodè. tanta tum quippe res agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vt nulla prorſus vrbanitas omni vacare peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo queat. Sed tamen ipſe loquebatur ex ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, &amp; per iocum illum à deliberatione, ſi qua foret, ſeriò Patres deterrere voluiſſet, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum dictis diſertiſſimis, ac re poſtea ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauit. Nam &amp; precibus a Deo inter Comitia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendebat aſſiduis, vt ſe à tam edito faſtigio procul auerteret; &amp; cùm Cardinalis quidam, grauitate, doctrina, religione ſpectatiſſimus ei diceret, in illo Conclaui, agi de ipſo iam coeptum ad Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euehendo, ſuamue propterea in opus tam ſalutare diligentiam, ſtudiumue deferret, non modo nullis hominem proſecutus eſt gratijs, veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> etiam enixè rogauit, ne, ſi ſaluum ſe cuperet, quicquam eiuſmodi, ſed alia omnia moliretur. quin articulatim, ac diſtinctè ſubiunxit, ſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò Principatum illum abnuere, &amp; ſic eſſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum, vt ne ſtipulam quidem, quae tum forrè ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebat humi, ad eum conſequendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honorem tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19250:83"/> loco vellet, aut commouere. Sed numqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in eo clarior apparuit huiuſce neglectus Imperij, quàm cum ſuo quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> munere perfunctus, quod Praefectos aliquos offendiſſet Regios, &amp; Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Magnos; admonituſue à familiari per lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras, vt videret etiam, atque etiam, ne quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret ſuis aliquando rationibus obfuturum, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere ſe gratiam amico pro beneuolentiae ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione reſpondit, verumtamen ipſo Sacerdotij principatu, ad cuius adeptionem ſui functionem muneris impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to futuram intelligeret inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretando, nihil omnino ſe commoueri; immo diſertè ſe Pontificem eſſe nolle. ſi quid grauius minis illis intentaretur, Marcelli Ceruini ſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potem eſſe minime degenerem, qui cùm Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis eſſet, Tridentum à Romano Pontifice ad cogendum, regendumue Concilium allegatus, ne propoſita quidem à Caeſarianis acerbiſſima nece deterreri potuit, aut impediri, quo minùs officio ſatisfaceret ſuo, idque perficeret, quod ab omnium Imperatore Deo ſibi demandatum eſſe intelligebat.</p>
                  <p>Commodum in hoc exemplum incidimus, quod non honoris tantummodo contemptionem habet, ſed etiam corporis, ac vitae. Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus enim extremo loco ſum, ipſam quoque vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam à Bellarmino fuiſſe neglectam, ac pro ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilo ductam; ne quid reſtaret, quod ille infra ſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19250:83"/> poſitum habere non videretur. Viro ſapienti, ac bono dolorem condonat A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtoteles de vitae ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctura, ſenſumue in ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o periculo mortis accer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biorem: quia cum illi vita ſit proba, cunctiſue virtutibus inſtructa, omnium intelligit maximè cùm moritur, &amp; quàm excellenti bono ſpolie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Sed neceſſe non habuit iſtam ab Ariſtotele veniam accipere Bellarminus, qui maiori cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date flagrabat interrumpendae vitae, quàm alij producendae. Intellectum id quidem ſemper eſt, ſed tum praeſertim, ac maximé, cùm in morbo, qui fuit illi poſtremus, ſiue caloris, aeſtuſue via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantulum aberraret interdum à mente, ſiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittente flagrantia, ſanitate vteretur integra, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae ab eo voces emittebantur aliae, niſi quae vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter è vitae ſtatione deceſlum efflagitarent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nemini, qui ſuas ei preces apud Caeleſtes offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, non reſpondit, aequi ſe boniue facere tam pium officium, ſed tamen id vnum excipere, ne ſibi vitam à Deo poſcerent, quam funditus ipſe repudiaret, ac nollet. Quin ab ipſo Pontifice Optimo, ac Maximo, ſuum ei ſtudium inter aras, ac ſacra pollicente, illa lege, conſilioue tam am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum ſe munus accipere velle profeſſus eſt, vt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiùs, ac citius è corporis vinculis auolaret in caelum, non vt ex eo mortis periculo liberaretur. Fuit illequidem in tota valetudinis regendae ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione facillimus, nec vmquam grauiùs inter cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19250:84"/> acerbitates, ac dolores eſt queſtus. ſed vnus tamen eius aliquando gemitus exauditus eſt, &amp; expoſtulatio non leuis, cum ſeptima poſt decubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum die habere ſe meliuſculè intellexit ex medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, qua die domum ſe ſuam (ſic enim ipſe caelum appellabat) commigraturum eſſe pro certo ſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerat. Illuxit denique tempus exoptatum, cùm admonitus, exiguum ſibi vitae ſpatium ſupereſſe, contineri non potuit, quin in ſumma illa confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti, afflicti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> corporis imbecillitate penè ſemiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus, atque intermortuus ter ingenti, claraue vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, O bonum nuncium exclamaret! Ne multa. commeatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac viaticum peregrinationi depoſcit idoneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: quod cùm humi ſtratus, &amp; ſic in genua quemadmodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poterat innixus excepiſſet, iteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lecto compoſitus, inter iucundiſſimas de caeleſti patria collocutiones, ac preces horam praeſtola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur extremam. quae cùm aliquando tandem adfuiſſet, crucem extemplò complexus arctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, ac velut illa comite facturus iter humeris, colloue leniter acclinans, haud multò poſt ſine laterum vexatione, ſine ſpiritus angore, ſine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauatione vultus, &amp; corporis, mortalitatem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleuit in terris, immortalitatem inter Caelites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choauit. vir omnino dignus, qui octogeſimo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer aetatis anno decendens, tamquam acerbo praeriperetur obitu, ſic omnium ordinum voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; luctu comploraretur. Populare prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19250:84"/> eſt, bouem vetulum non lugeri, in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bene ſenes, &amp; grandiores aetate conueniens; quorum exceſſus quia tempeſtiuus eſſe videtur omnibus, amicorum luctu vacat, &amp; complorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne domeſticorum. ſed hoc dictum alioqui veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diuturno comprobatum experimento in Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini funere deprehendimus falſum, qui &amp; tam ſenex ploratus ab omnibus eſt, &amp; ſi ad plures quoque prouectus fuiſſet annos, ſemper exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matus fuiſſet immaturè decedere. Nimirum, vt vetus quidam poëta loquitur, Conſules fiunt quota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis, &amp; noui Proconſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es. Sed (non dicam equidem quod apud eundem ſequitur, Solus, aut Rex, aut Poëta non quotannis naſcitur. Rex e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim quotidie naſcitur ex Regibus, &amp; poëtarum natio plus etiam quàm vellemus, in Republica ſoboleſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) ſed dicam inquam id quod ipſa res eſt, nec in idonea laude verebor inuidia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Solus Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mino ſimilis ordinis ampliſſimi Senator, ita doctus, ac ſapiens, ita modeſtus, ac moderatus, religioſus, ac pius, ita Reipublicae ſalutaris, non modo non quotannis naſcitur, ſed requiretur in annos plurimos, &amp; longa poſt ſaecula deſiderabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Non tamen eius à nobis vmquam deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Non tamen eius à nobis vmquam deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur auxilium, non fides, non Eccleſiae patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinium, ac tutela; cuius militantis ipſe, dum viueret, tam praeclara ſtipendia meruit, cuius o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantis, vita iam functus, &amp; triumphum capit,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19250:85"/> &amp; obtinet gloriam. Excurrit ille nunc inter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elices animas, Ambroſios, Auguſtinos, alioſue mortis beneficio triumphantes, ac liberos: reſpicit è caelo relicta, videt nos alta nocte circumdatos, &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis perfuſam radijs aciem promittit in ſpatia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am vaſta terrarum. Suas adeo partes intelligit eſſe, pro Chriſtiana Republica non iam amplius Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbae gemitum dare, quod ſcripto libello fecit in lugentium campis, ſed per aduocationem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe, atque intercedere; quod &amp; praeſtitit olim viuens in terris, &amp; nunc praeſtare multò facilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè poteſt in triumphantium Concilio colloca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:85"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:86"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19250:86"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
